<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The replie of Iohn Darrell, to the answer of Iohn Deacon, and Iohn Walker, concerning the doctrine of the possession and dispossession of demoniakes</title>
            <author>Darrel, John, b. ca. 1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844944</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844944</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1233:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The replie of Iohn Darrell, to the answer of Iohn Deacon, and Iohn Walker, concerning the doctrine of the possession and dispossession of demoniakes</title>
                  <author>Darrel, John, b. ca. 1562.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 50, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by the English secret press?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Deacon, John and Walker, John.  A summarie answere to al the material points in any of Master Darel his bookes.</note>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Deacon, John, 17th cent. --  Summarie answere to al the material points in any of Master Darel his bookes --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Demoniac possession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Exorcism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:1"/>
            <p>THE REPLIE OF IOHN DARRELL, TO THE AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SWER OF IOHN DEACON, AND <hi>Iohn Walker,</hi> concerning the doctrine of the Poſſeſſion and Diſpoſſeſsion of Demoniakes.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſiaſtes 4. 1.</bibl>
               <p>I turned, and conſidered all the oppreſsions that are wrought vnder the ſun, and behold, the teares of the oppreſſed, &amp; none comforteth them: and loe the ſtrength is of the hand of them that oppreſſe them, and none comforteth them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHERS AND BRETHREN, the Paſtors and Teachers in the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Grace and peace be multiplied in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>IT had bene to be wiſhed (right Reuerend &amp; beloued in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt) that ſome queſtion ariſing of late, as you know, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Diſpoſſeſsion of diuels in theſe times by faſting and prayer,</hi> the ſame might haue bene propounded, examined, and decided in your lawful aſſembly. For your ſenſes being exerciſed in the knowledge of God his truth, and your minds enlightened with continuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Church, would eaſily haue diſcerned the ſtampe of the Sanctuarie: and this iudiciall determination of yours, woulde (no doubt) either haue preuented, or ſtayed at leaſt much violent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, manie impious aſſertions, and great diſtractions among the people, which not able to iudge of the ſubſtance of things, ſtand amazed at the vaine ſound and multitude of words. But as this happineſſe hath bin much wiſhed in like caſe heretofore, ſo neuer could it be leſſe hoped for then now, when our ſinnes haue brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed new life into the dead carkeſſe of Antichriſt, whereby hee ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles vp on his feete afreſh, and begins to ſtrout amongſt vs againe in terrible ſort. yet notwithſtanding your ioint conſents cannot be had, I thought it meet to offer this Reioynder to your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeuerally, holding it moſt requiſite that you the ſame parties ſhould alſo heare Truth ſpeake in her iuſt defence, before whom, and to whom, ſhee hath beene ſlaundered moſt ſhamefully. But what Truth is able to pleade for her ſelfe ſhall more fully appeare in the Treatiſe following: now onely ſhe craueth, that as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> iudged of <hi>Iulian</hi> by the wagging of his head, ſo by theſe two Epiſtles of theirs, one to your ſelues, the other to the Reader, it would pleaſe you to regard of what diſpoſition theſe Anſwerers bee.</p>
            <p>In their Epiſtle to you (reuerend brethren) you ſhall beholde them falſe in pretence, vntrue in their words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ridiculouſly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant. For pretence, they make ſhew of great promptneſſe with all humilitie <hi>to ſubmit their opinions to your graue and learned cenſures.</hi> And who would not eſteeme this lowlineſſe, as if the men were lately deſcended from heauen? But alas, they know your pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:9803:3"/>
cenſure is not to be feared: more waightie occaſions haue not hetherto procured it: and what any of you ſhall pronounce pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, wil be but one Doctors opinion with them. Their practiſe makes this plaine in their <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> where teſtimonie as cleare as the ſunne light alleaged, how the Church both ancient, and preſent hath demeaned her ſelfe in like actions, they not hauing one word of probabilitie to reply, would ſhift off the matter with ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe outfacing. Is it likely nowe (worthie Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) theſe men would reuerence your authoritie, who reiect without bluſhing the authoritie of them, whom all the learned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedly reuerence? This profeſsion then is but a meere abuſe, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing onely for a maske to hide the deformity of their natural coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. And as they would carrie a faire colour of that, they neuer purpoſe to doe, ſo alſo they be no leſſe vntrue in reporting things alreadie paſt. They tell you, How <hi>inſolently we denied the Chriſtian conference they prefered vs:</hi> whereas they neuer profered me any: and as for <hi>M. Moore,</hi> they comming to him, promiſing to confer the next morning, neuer came to him afterwards: thinking it better to cracke their credit in breaking that promiſe, then to ſtand to their word, &amp; receiue a foyle in the bickering. So they talk of <hi>a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with me, offered to my ſpeciall friends:</hi> when neither friend not foe kuew where I was: when alſo had they knowne, and ſignified vnto me this profered conference, I might with ſmall ſecuritie to my perſon haue conferred with them, notwithſtanding their profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red bond. Whereby you may ſee that occaſion was rather ſought to blind the world with, then that any <hi>conference</hi> was ſoundly intended. In like manner they affirming, that diſpoſſeſſion in theſe times by faſting &amp; prayer <hi>be miracles:</hi> that they bee vrged as <hi>neceſſary to ſupport our Relgion: that there is no difference between them wrought in the church of god amongst vs, &amp; theſe done in Antichriſts kingdom: that the dealers, in theſe actions are to be matched with Bròwniſts &amp; Hackets:</hi> are aſſertions of ſuch nature as might with good reaſon, were they true, enrage your meek &amp; patient ſpirits with indignation: ſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you heare their principal end in publiſhing <hi>theſe Counſels of God lately reuealed vnto them concerning theſe incricate queſtions</hi> (for ſo they <note place="margin">Anſwer. page 95</note>ſpeake of theſe fancies or rather frenſies of theirs in the Treatiſe following) was forſooth to <hi>accompliſh the peace of Ieruſalem.</hi> Are nouelties peaceable? Innouations fit for quiet? Doctrines neuer heard of before, procurers of concord? O bleſſed peacemakers, which would ſoulder vp the breaches and diſagreements of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
<pb facs="tcp:9803:3"/>
with <hi>latelie reucaled counſels.</hi> Thus they dare toyour faces poure forth their vntruths, not onely in matter of faith, wherein none but ſome ſpeciall perſons could conuict them: but alſo in doctrines, whoſe falſhood your ſelues are beſt able of all other to deſcry as ſoone as you heare them. And is not their arrogancy worthy to be laughed at (but that your manner is rather to bewaile mens folly) when they would be <hi>Magiſtri ſententiarum,</hi> &amp; haue their Diſcourſes Dictates for young ſtudents in diuinitie? It were hanſom ſure to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a Sow ſit with a diſtaffe teaching the fine Ladies to ſpin: that the Crow ſhould inſtruct the young Nighttingales to ſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that the Conduites in Cheape ſhould be fed from the publike draynes &amp; ſinkes of the citie. But could they bee content to be directours only to the younger ſtudents? Theſe myſteries of theirs are <hi>an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible truth,</hi> as they ſay, &amp; <hi>Counſels of god lately reuealed vnto them,</hi> as you heard euen now. And therfore your ſelues, learned Fathers, though much trauelled in the ſacred ſciptures, greatly read in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent writers, &amp; acquainted with later monuments of knowledge &amp; experience of all kinde, yet hitherto in theſe poyntes you know nothing: &amp; if you purpoſe hereafter to vnderſtand any thing, you muſt ſucke it onely from the breaſts of theſe <hi>late Reuelations.</hi> In which regarde it may very well bee, theſe <hi>Anſwerers</hi> could greatly reioyce (as alſo they profeſſe) if it might pleaſe any of you to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute them, becauſe they thinke theſelues on ſo ſure a ground, &amp; are tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as it ſeemeth with an imagination of that glory, which they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſhould gaine by your foile &amp; diſcredit. Whether they wil accept ſuch a labour in good part or no, you ſhall haue experience by this I haue performed. Their former pretences make me to feare this outſide of theirs is but ouercaſt with their wonted perietting.</p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the Reader they ſay that <hi>I haue very vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably endeuoured to wound</hi> S. H. (whom els where they call <hi>S. Harſnet vnto death for his dutifull Diſcouerie.</hi> I maruell they are not aſhamed to call it <hi>a dutifull diſcorerie,</hi> ſeeing the drift of it is, to proue, <hi>that I taught Sommers to counterfeit,</hi> wherof themſelues acquit me, as ye ſhall heare forthwith. What <hi>dutie</hi> performed he to God or man, in ſlaundering the rare workes of god, &amp; his neightbour? Or do they in commending ſuch a Diſcouerie. It is true that by my <hi>Detection</hi> I endeuoured <hi>to wound S. H. mortally,</hi> ſo as he ſhould neuer be able to riſe vp any more <hi>for counterſeiting &amp; my teaching to counterfeit:</hi> but not with ſword, nor ſpeare, onely with the dart of Truth. And I thinke it is as true that I haue <hi>wounded him to death.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9803:4"/>
Had not his wounds bene mortall, or at leaſtwiſe incurable, they had beene healed by this, and we had ſeene him the ſecond time in the field. Otherwiſe we muſt deem him for a coward, that encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth not his enemie being often chalenged. This is the excellency &amp; power of truth that ſhee ſubdueth all thoſe that riſe vp in armes againſt her, &amp; they that take part with her, do at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, as being more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conquerors. They blame my <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlets as ful of vnſound &amp; abſurd poſitions.</hi> I wil not confirme in this place, what is els where ſet down, but refer to your Iudgement whether by the former <hi>Suruery,</hi> &amp; the following <hi>Reply</hi> it doth not appeare that many <hi>ſuch poſitions</hi> haue iſſued from their owne heads, &amp; that this charge may be turned vpon their owne pates. For <hi>mater,</hi> they charge my writings with <hi>want of Methode:</hi> to bee alſo <hi>ſchiſmaticall</hi> and <hi>Eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gmaticall.</hi> Touching the <hi>Methode,</hi> I hope your patience hath beene contented with the order of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> diuided into three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches &amp; each part proſecuted firſt with reaſons confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: &amp; after by remoouing ſuch doubtes as might ſeeme to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it. And as for <hi>Schiſme,</hi> I teach no Latelie <hi>reuealed counſels, nor my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dialog. Diſcourſ. Epiſt. to the Reader in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</note>
               <hi>priuate opinion concerning the poſſeſſion &amp; diſpoſſeſsion of diuels.</hi> Both which theſe men confeſſe they do, but what hath ben reuealed and held from the beginning &amp; confirmed euer ſince by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent: whereas if their doctrines be <hi>their owne priuate opinions, and Latelie reuealed,</hi> they bee New. If New, not eſtabliſhed by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Scriptures &amp; the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; if not eſtabliſhed, it is <hi>ſchiſme</hi> at the leaſt, for any thing I can conceiue, to publiſh &amp; maintein them. Concerning <hi>Enigmatiall</hi> handling, your owne profiting by reading may beſt be Iudge. It was not my purpoſe, neyther, is it my skill to write ridles: Yet becauſe they complaine of darkenes I haue now ſo indeuored my ſelfe, that I hope they may ſpell my meaning, if they put on their ſpectacles Moreouer they accuſe the <hi>ſpirit wherwith my pamphlets are indited, to be ſenſuall &amp; deuilish,</hi> as giuen to <hi>Rayling, Contradiction, &amp; Diſobedience.</hi> Horrible, indeed is the ſinne of <hi>Rayling.</hi> But iuſt &amp; plaine reprouing with theſe men is railing: Curing is killing, &amp; whatſoeuer ſmarteth in the ſore, is dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 24. 17.</note>poyſon. <hi>The morning to the adulterer, is as the ſhadow of death.</hi> The vlcerous patient crveth out on euery touch of the Chirurgion, as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 12.</note>at moſt rough &amp; vnaduiſed handling. It is no meruail if the <hi>Cretians can</hi> not endure to be told, they are <hi>lyars, eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l beaſts &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w bellies</hi> &amp; that ſharpe reproofe be reuiled by ſuch, as altogether in tollerable, barbarous, and inhumane. Yet further behold <hi>I</hi> beſeech you in
<pb facs="tcp:9803:4"/>
themſelues, how deſtitute they are of Gods feare in this behalfe: how voyd of the common wiſedom of men: &amp; how ſtrongly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with that ſelf ſame itching diſeaſe they charge me withall. It is great want of reuerence towards god to defame others falſely, &amp; that againſt their owne conſcience, as they doe me moſt opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly throughout their whole treatiſes. It is exceeding ſolly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him by forged crimes, which can repay them againe with moſt true crimes, with publike crimes, with hainons crimes. And is it not an incurable itching which muſt needes be clawing, till thier own fleſh be rent from their bones? Theſe mens deſire of ſcratching was ſo hot, that poſſibly they could not hold their fingers, though they were guilty to them ſelues, how deare it might coſt them: wherein notwithſtanding I haue ſpared them, being aſhamed in playne tearmes to vtter that which they haue not bene aſhamed to do. Concerning the <hi>Contradictions</hi> they would thruſt vpon me, you will eaſily perceiue in the <hi>Reply,</hi> how partly they ſpring from their owne ignorance, as if I cal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>thing <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>ſupernaturall,</hi> then muſt there needs be a <hi>Contradiction:</hi> partly from their adding, detracting, and changing my words at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ir pleaſure, which they haue done aduiſedly and purpoſely, whereby their ſin is increaſed. And as for <hi>Diſobedience by my ſtriring againſt the ſentence of the High Commiſſion:</hi> is it <hi>a rebellious and vnruly proceeding</hi> according to the commandement &amp; example of Chriſt Ieſus to iuſtifie the works of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 25. 30<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>god being ſlaundered, or yet for one-to complaine of wrong. For marke I beſeech you how in this place they affirming, <hi>that by due order of law wee were conuented, conuicted, apprehended, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, by ſentence of Iuſtice defintiuely conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned for groſſe malefactors, &amp; adiudged to priſon:</hi> yet in their <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> haue giuen this teſtimonie of me, that they did <hi>not ſo much as ſuſpect any precompacted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſederacy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Diale. Diſ. pag. <hi>352.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>betweene me and the boy, that all acquainted with my former ſynceritie and vpright cariage are free from ſuch a perſwaſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the graceles boy did graceleſly counterfet, and my ſelf did only erre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iudgement, and not of any purpoſe in practiſe at all.</hi> By the witnes therfore of theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if the high Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion paſſed any ſuch <hi>ſeutence</hi> againſt vs they did vs open iniurv: &amp; I truſt oppreſſed inuocents may haue this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at leaſt to bewaile their greife. But neither hath the Commiſſion awarded any ſuch ſentence, and theſe men haue done a double notable wrong in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſlauncering both the Commiſtion, and vs.</p>
            <p>To ſhut vp all, they would boodwink the reader with their godly iealouſie ouer him, pretending they labour to prepaire him for one
<pb facs="tcp:9803:5"/>
husband, and to preſent <hi>him as a pure virgin to Chriſt.</hi> But this office <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note>belongeth to the Biſhop that is biameles, and is the husband of one wife, &amp;c. as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. And therfore if the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader ſhould looke for grapes from theſe thomes, he ſhould be deceaued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this Epiſtle then to the <hi>Reader</hi> is fraught with the ſame vertues of Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, of forging, of pride (though with ſome larger addition) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the former, reuerend Fathers and brethren, was to you. And therefore howſoeuer they thinke, I wil anſwere them as <hi>Hildebrand</hi> did, <hi>Abbas Caſsinenſis, frater nimtum tardasti: Deere brethren, you have beene ſomewhat too ſlow</hi> in publiſhing your <hi>Dialogicall Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> yet I doubt not, but both you, and I, will with one conſent, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returne the contrarie to them, <hi>Et vos Disputatores nimium feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtis: And you, O Diſcourſers, haue made too much haſte.</hi> For had you trauelled as long, as the Elephant in bringing forth her young, yet the birth of ſuch monſtrous deuiſes, ſo ignorant, ſo erroneous, ſo ſlaunderons, ſo impious, had bene abortiue, vntimely, and too ſoon. For this cauſe I haue dealt more roundly and freely with them, then otherwiſe I would haue done with ordinarie men. They could not poſsibly be wakened out of ſo ſtrong an Apoplexie, but by bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feathers and ſhoo-ſoles vnder their noſes: neither would the Reader haue bene ſufficiently warned to eſchew their fraud, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the trumpet had ſounded ſhrill in his eares.</p>
            <p>And whereas ſome of you, reuerend and beloued brethren, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, and verie truly, that their bookes were vnworthy the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, did thereupon earneſtly diſſwade me from writing: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 10.</note>So alſo was the doctrine of thoſe <hi>vaine talkers, Paul</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to <hi>Titus,</hi> vnworthy to be confuted, yet the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Their mouthes muſt be ſtopped.</hi> And how? by <hi>conuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing,</hi> as there followeth. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 24</note>What could be more palpablie falſe, then that of the Phariſees, <hi>Hee caſteth out diuels, through Beelzebub the Prince of diuels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting our Sauiour did conuince the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Euen ſo did <hi>S. Peter</hi> thoſe who <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 13</note>
               <hi>mocked,</hi> and ſaid the Apoſtles <hi>were full of new wine,</hi> when the holy Ghoſt in that wonderful maner fel vpon them. In priuate commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>A foole is to be anſwered according to his folly:</hi> but if in pub like among the preſſe, in the higheſt places of the citie, or entrings of the gates, where wiſdomes voice ſhould be heard, a foole chance to babble, and vtter that is dangerous to the ſimple, which theſe <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> haue done, then is the folly of a foole to bee throughly diſcouered, and layd open to the viewe of all men. <hi>The fooliſh</hi> (of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14, 15</note>which number are the moſt) <hi>will beleeue euery thing,</hi> be it neuer ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9803:5"/>
falſe, be it neuer ſo abſurd, neuer ſo ſottiſh &amp; ridiculous, ſpecially if it be countenanced with Authority, as are the <hi>Dialog call Diſcourſes.</hi> For this reaſon, euen to keepe the ſimple from error, who are ſo eaſilie ſeduced, notwithſtanding the vnworthines of theſe <hi>Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> there is cauſe ſomething ſhould be ſayd in anſwere vnto them, by my ſelfe or other. Neither doe I doubt but theſe my rude lines will (by the bleſsing of God) be effectuall to recouer thoſe which through their verbal writings be falne from the truth, to ſtrengthen ſuch as be wauering, and to ſtabliſh them which more firmely hold the truth. If this ſucceſſe follow, I ſhall haue no cauſe to repent me of my paines, nor any other to account the ſame ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>Now therfore, brethren, I beleech you know theſe diſturbers, be not deceiued by their ouercaſting and ſmoothing. Examine what they ſay, before ye beleeue them. Anb albeit your authority is not able to bridle them (the more is our griefe, and the miſerie of our Church) yet auoid their doctrines in your ſelues, and in your people. I beſeech you alſo, as your occaſions may ſerue, admoniſh them: that yet in want of a publike degree, they may gather by you ſeuerally what is the iudgement of all, and be therby aſhamed and reclaimed, if ſo the Lord in mercy pleaſe. Litle needes ſuch conflict in theſe times wherin that antichriſt of Rome extreme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly rageth, as now entring his laſt triall. But we muſt haue fightings <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 5.</note>without and feares within: open wars with the preiſts and leſuites, the ſeruants of Antichiriſt, and many priuate grieuances by ſuch as would bee counted of the houſhold of faith. It behooues vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brethren, to put on the armor of righteouſnes on the right <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 7</note>hand, and on the left, that wee may manfully defend &amp; mainteine the holy truth in all her bounds &amp; limits vnuiolated ſyncere where by the puritie of Religion may ſtill bee continued, and all errour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anoying either vs or our poſteritie after vs. The god of mercy, peace and truth confirme and eſtabliſh our heartes, that we may fight the good fight, like good ſoldiers of Ieſus Chriſt, and quit our ſelues like men: holding faith &amp; a good conſcience, to the glory of his name, &amp; euerlaſting comfort of our owne ſoules, through Ieſus our Lord and onely Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your fellow ſeruant in the worke of the Goſpell. Iohn Darrell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9803:6"/>
            <head>THE REPLIE TO THE FIRST DIALOGVE.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 3, 9. 10.</note> IT is a cunning ſleight to beguile the ſimple with, in propounding to ſatiſfy the world for any thing that hath bene ſayd concerning the poynts and parties controuerted, wholy to omit the books cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledthe <hi>Triall,</hi> the <hi>Detection,</hi> the <hi>Narration</hi> of ſeuen poſſeſſed in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> contayning in them matters of fact, and onely to bend your forces againſt one Treatiſe called <hi>The Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. The reaſon of which <hi>omiſſion,</hi> Chriſtian Reader, is this. To diſproue things done, ſo euidently knowne to ſo many eye-witneſſes, were all one as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that white is blacke, that fire is Ice, that it is dark night in the cleare ſunſhine, which whoſo ſhould endeuor would rather be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of all a mad ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaine any credit to his cauſe. But in points and controuerſies of <hi>doctrine</hi> there was more hope to deceiue. For here through multitude of words, ambiguous tearmes, fraudulent courſes of reaſoning, falſe coloured ſentences, wreſted and miſtcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued ſcriptures, abuſed authorities of famous men, and ſuch other deuiſes, not onely the ignorant &amp; vnable to ſearch the truth ſhould be blinded, but alſo many learned, which before had not welghed theſe thinges, neither perhaps would take the paines to ſift and try them to the proofe, might be ſtriken with ſome amaſe &amp; doubt. Only they whoſe iudgments are ſeaſoned with ſound vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which at firſt ſight are able to diſcerne the cro oked writings of peeniſh and fooliſh ſophiſters, and know without book the ſcope of moſt mens writings in account amongſt the learned, woulde giue true ſentence of the cauſe, and condemne the ſe opinions of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and errour. But the number of ſuch is ſmal, and therfore by theſe <hi>Anſwerers</hi> was leſſe regarded. This, whatſoeuer they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, was the true ground of their choiſe, yet though they <hi>will not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</note>
               <hi>meddle with the Triall, and Detection,</hi> they muſt <hi>bicker a blow or two with the Epiſtles of both.</hi> To let paſſe the diſgraces, wherewith they lade them: for the <hi>Triall</hi> I may ſay (for therof am not I author) I doubt not but iudiciall men wil acknowledge more ſound lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ſome fewe lines of it, then is in the whole bundle of your fooliſh <hi>Diſcourſes.</hi> To come to that which is material, you charge the <hi>Triall</hi> but with two things, &amp; in this charge make four lies, ſuch is your compendious facultie. Firſt, ſay you, <hi>it matcheth your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb facs="tcp:9803:7"/>
miracle, with the true miracles of Chriſt.</hi> The words of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> ſpeaking to the <hi>L. Popham,</hi> bee theſe, <hi>And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. pag. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>as highly the glory of Chriſt our Sauiour, as it doth the credit of a faithfull miniſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Is here any compariſon of miracles? Is here any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of miracles at all? Doth it ſay any more, but this cauſe being about a worke done in the name of Chriſt, doth as highly concerne <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>4.</hi> Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls trial in the Epiſt. pa. <hi>8</hi>
               </note>his glory, as my credit? Again, ſay you, <hi>the prelats are charged with the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Thus ſpeaketh the Epiſtle, <hi>that the prelates (which now ſet themſelues againſt diſpoſſeſſion) be guiltie of this vnpardo nable ſin, I wil not ſay.</hi> If I wil not ſay, be I do ſay, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prelats are charged with this ſin. Out of this branch ſpring two other, That you report the Epiſtle to labour <hi>the L. Chiefe Iuſtice to recouer himſelf with ſpeed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fearefull ſin, wherunto it ſeemes he is fearefully falling: and that he would reuerſe iudgement paſſed againſt me.</hi> He which writ the Epiſtle did not dote, as you do, to entitle his Honour, <hi>an vpright, and worthy,</hi> and <hi>a righteous iudge,</hi> to deſire and vrge his Lordſhip, <hi>to releeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the oppreſſed innocent,</hi> ſpecially, <hi>to take to heart the ſlanders giuen out of the works of God:</hi> and within a few lines after to place him in the verie brinke of reprobation. Neither doth he perſwade to a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing of iudgment</hi> (for there was none paſſed, as the Authour knew well enough) but to a <hi>ſecond hearing, as Felix heard Paul the ſecond time.</hi> Now then let the Reader tell me, if you bee not pithie lyars, that can comprehend ſo many in ſo little roome.</p>
            <p>For my <hi>Detection</hi> you charge the <hi>Title</hi> as <hi>vndutifull against her Maieſties iudiciall proceedings,</hi> for that it is ſo ſharpe againſt <hi>M. Harſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> booke. It is more then I knowe, or can beleeue, that her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie commanded <hi>M. Harſnet</hi> to write: or that her Right Hono. Counſell inioined him ſo much, or that the high Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion laid this vpon him. It may be, if his owne vainglorious humor, which euer tooke pleaſure to be biting of others, did not prick him forward to this buſines, yet that the <hi>B.</hi> his maiſter, of his priuat authoritie, did ſet him his taſke, toſalue this owne credit, and of ſuch as had ioined in diſgracing the truth. But I hope one may reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome priuat actions of the <hi>B.</hi> without any vndtifulnes to her maieſties procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. You then are malicious pikthanks, which haue nothing in your mouthes, but <hi>Ad leones, ad leones, He is not Ceſars friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 5.</note> For the <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> you charge me <hi>with reviling the B.</hi> I anſwere, It was not anie contempt or malice towards his perſon, or forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of any dutie to authoritie, that moued me to ſuch ſeueritie, as I vſed, but onely feare leaſt otherwiſe <hi>I</hi> ſhould haue failed in dutie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9803:7"/>
towards God. <hi>Thoſe which ſinne,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>reproue openly:</hi> And <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 20 <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.</note>
               <hi>reproue with all authoritie.</hi> And when I heare <hi>Iobn Baptiſt</hi> calling the Phari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ees <hi>Deceiuers,</hi> and <hi>Generations of vipers:</hi> when I heare our Sauiour moſt ſharply reprouing them by the names of <hi>Perſecutors, ſerpents, generation of vipers, the children of hell, painted ſepulchers,</hi> and ſuch like: And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Elymas, O full of all ſubtilty, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 9. 10. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1, 12. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18 <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 17</note>
               <hi>all miſchiefe, the child of the diuell, and enemy of all righteouſneſſe:</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alſo falſe prophets <hi>Dogges,</hi> and the Cretians <hi>beaſts:</hi> yea when I heare <hi>Eliiah</hi> call <hi>Ahab, the troubler of Iſrael:</hi> our Sauiour tearme <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod a foxe, Paul</hi> entituling <hi>Ananias a painted wall,</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> by the name of a <hi>Lyon:</hi> I heſe and manie ſuch other places of practiſe, giue me ſome light for vnderſtanding the precept, and teach me, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in my priuate cauſe I am to vſe all mildeneſſe and gentleneſſe, yet when the Lords truth is intereſſed and ſlaundered, his greate mercie obſcured, and that of purpoſe and wilfully, neither one <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> by <hi>Elymas</hi> hindered, but manie thouſands turned backe from beleeuing his works, from praiſing him for them, and profiting by them, in this caſe the man of authority is no leſſe to be ſtricken with the edge of reproofe, then he that is in inferiour place. Nay, rather the publike perſon, then the priuate man, by how much his example is more dangerous, either forcing or alluring great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes to imbrace his errour. And this doth not hinder but with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</note>&amp; <hi>Stephen, and our Sauiour himſelfe, and all the holy martyrs of God, wee ſhould pray for our perſecuters, and bleſſe them which curſe vs:</hi> for reproofe and hatred be not neceſſarily linked together, but Reproofe is a notable remedie to preſerue from hatred, according to that the Lord ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy beart, but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Louit.</hi> 19. 1</note>
               <hi>thou ſhalt plainly rebuke thy neighbour, and ſuffer him not to ſinne.</hi> But this is your maner, to huddle vp all things in a confuſed heape to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and that which is ſpoken with certaine prouiſoes and limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to alleage it as a bare and ſimple commaund. Thus much for the Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 7.</note> Yet before you come to the Treatiſe, you will <hi>admoniſh the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of two cunning ſleights of legerdemainc, practiſed by me, throughout that my Pamphlet: whereof the firſt is, That I haue ſlily ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſlipped what is materiall in M. Harſnets Diſcouery, as, to make good that distinction of Mirandum &amp; Miraculum, which he hath daſhed to nothing.</hi> I anſwere, that as becommeth true natural Leopards, you cannot change your skinne, but you muſt needs be lying heere, as almoſt euerie where elſe: for I haue replied to M. <hi>Harſnet</hi> out of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Danaeus,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9803:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">Detection, pag. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> ſhewing an apparant difference betweene a Wonder, and a Miracle.</hi> And further haue I anſwered in ſuruey of your tenth Dialogue: from whence I pray you tell <hi>M. Harſnet,</hi> that if he remember the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Species,</hi> he may feele with his finger that a <hi>Wonder</hi> and a <hi>Miracle</hi> be not all one. And if this will not ſuffice him, demaund of him, whether Antichriſt by the power of Satan worketh not wonders: and whether he eſteeme all thoſe wonders to be true miracles. And as touching your ſelues who accord with <hi>M. Harſnet</hi> herein, what ſay you to theſe words of your owne? <hi>The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dialog. pag.</hi> 209. &amp; 310.</note>
               <hi>diuell may worke wonders, as Simon Magus hath done: but hee can ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect no miracles.</hi> And in another place. <hi>A thing effected by eſſentiall meanes, howſoeuer it may be a wonder, yet no miracle in any respect.</hi> How can you poſsibly free your ſelues here from a contradiction? And this is my reply to your firſt inſtance. Againe, ſay you, <hi>M. Harſnet accuſing verie orderly by Sommers testimony, mine owne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, and ſeuerall depoſitions: this his materiall proceeding is pretermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſilence.</hi> What? haue I written a <hi>Detection of his lying Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie,</hi> and haue touched nothing concerning <hi>Sommers teſtimonic, mine owne anſwers, and the ſeuerall depoſitions?</hi> Then haue I written nothing at all: For there be ſcarce anie lines in it, which concerne not one of theſe three. But thereof let the world Iudge. I can ſay no more. I hope I haue ſhewed how indirect a courſe it is, that <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> by threats, flatterings, and promiſes of maintenance ſhoulde firſt he brought to accuſe himſelfe, after me, and then to witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: that mine owne anſwers ſhould be curtalled, and ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched after the <hi>Diſcouerers</hi> pleaſures: that the depoſitions which were againſt their likings ſhould be ſuppreſſed, and others publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſo far forth, as might giue occaſion of doubt to the Reader. What dare not you auouch, which are ſo bold to affrme that, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the contrary appeares in euery mans hand? If your meaning were that in ſome particular I haue pretermitted this, which your words will not beare, then you ſhould haue done well to haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that Particular, as the nature of an Inſtance requireth, which ſeeing you haue not done, it is thereby plaine, your ſelues be rather guiltie of <hi>legerdemaine,</hi> then L Thoſe pages which you quote in the margine, I grant I paſſed ouer, for that they concerne others, and <note place="margin">S. Harſ. Diſc. <hi>28. 29.</hi>
               </note>not my ſelfe, as alſo becauſe the matter was friuolous and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy anſwere, as may there appeare, vrging the being of a thing by no other reaſon, but becauſe ſuch a thing might be. But marke what a faire threed theſe men haue ſpun, and how ſeeking to diſcredite
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9803:8"/>
my <hi>Detection,</hi> they haue brought not a little credite vnto it. For I will hence proue, that in my <hi>Detection</hi> I haue not let paſſe <hi>one mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall point of M. Harſnets Diſcouery</hi> vnanſwered: and namely thus. If <hi>Darrell</hi> haue in his <hi>Detection</hi> let goe anie materiall point of the <hi>Diſcouery</hi> vnanſwered, then would the <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> haue giuen ſome inſtances of ſuch omiſsion, where they endeuor to proue the ſame by inſtances: But the <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> inſtancing to that end, haue giuen not ſo much as one inſtance of ſuch omiſsion: Ergo <hi>Darrell</hi> in his <hi>Detection</hi> hath not let goe any one materiall point in the <hi>Diſcouery</hi> vnanſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 8. 9.</note> My ſecond cunning ſleight by your ſaying is, that I <hi>diſgrace by all meanes Sommers teſtimonie, produced againſt me but extoll it for me, vpholding by it the ſignes of Poſſeſsion &amp; Diſpoſſeſsion.</hi> That no credit is to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his lying teſtimony, I auouch it indeed in the place by you cited: but where do I <hi>vphold the ſignes of poſſeſsion &amp; dispoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion by Sommers his teſtimonie,</hi> wherewith you charge me? why do not you alſo cite ſome place for this? You thought if one part of your aſſertion were true, the Reader would pardon you for the reſt. It is ſuch nouelty for you to ſpeake truth, that any litle is to be accepted at your hands.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of the <hi>Detection</hi> you come to the <hi>Narration,</hi> the proofe wherof you will not haue to depend vpon report of the fact <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 10. 11.</note>but <hi>vpon continuance of Eſſentiall Poſſeſſions and Diſpoſſeſſions in theſe times.</hi> A ridiculous thing, and to be hiſſed at. The reaſon why you eſchew to deale againſt <hi>matter of fact,</hi> I haue ſufficently declared in the beginning. Wel I wil follow you in your courſe, &amp; come to your <hi>Anſwere</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Which treatiſe, to admit ſuch an <hi>hotchpotch</hi> as you ſay, <hi>(though</hi> ſober men <hi>will iudge</hi> it, ſet downe in ſuch order as is conuenient) it is not for euery one to cooke his matters ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially as your Diſcourſing gallimaufrey is: but the more skil it wantes, the more credit for truth it ought to haue, ſeeing it raſteth ſimply as bare nature giues, without commendation of any ſlibber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauce. Firſt for Eſſentiall poſſeſsion you reproue me or at leaſt <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſtes,</hi> for arguing from the word <hi>Poſſeſsion out of the Geneuah tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 12. 13.</note>whereas I no where, nor any man elſe, inferre eſſentiall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie from the word <hi>Poſſeſsion,</hi> as I haue ſhewed in the Suruey of your <hi>Dialog. Diſcourſe:</hi> yet is the ſame confuted by the <hi>Originall,</hi> by <hi>Eraſmus, Beza, Caſtalio,</hi> and <hi>Montanus.</hi> But this was your volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie perhaps, before you came to your muſicke, now let vs beare your ſet and meditated ſong. Wheras I argue a poſſeſsion thus: <hi>The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9803:9"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 13. 14.</note> actions</hi> or <hi>paſrions which the parties endured were ſupernaturall, and therefore proceeded from ſupernaturall cauſes.</hi> You deny <hi>the actions were ſupernaturall,</hi> and that for three reaſons. Firſt, <hi>Naturall cauſes haue had more wonderful effects:</hi> which I think I haue ſufficiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the beginning of your ſeuenth Dialogue. Now therefore in one word, Is nothing ſupernaturall in any creature, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by anie other worke in nature? Then the foming, wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the breaking of chaines aſunder, reported of Demoniakes in the Goſpel were not ſupernaturall, becauſe ſomething more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <note place="margin">Dialog. Diſ. <hi>204.</hi>
               </note>may come from a naturall cauſe: as that mentioned by you of the little fiſh <hi>Echneis,</hi> which (being but halfe a foote long) if ſhee but once cleaue to the ſide of a ſhip, wil compel it perforce to ſtand ſtill, notwithſtanding the violence of the wind or oare. I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med to heare men thus abſurd. You might haue conſidered, had your wits beene your owne, that theſe actions or paſsions are not therefore ſupernaturall, and ſo called, becauſe they are more won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derfull then anie thing iſſuing from nature, which a naturall would ſcarce affirme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but partly becauſe they are (for the moſt part) aboue that, and more wonderfull then the nature of man can ſend forth: and partly in reſpect of the ſupernatural cauſe from which they did proceed, namely, the diuel. Secondly, ſay you, <hi>One cauſe may bring forth ſundry effects, and one effect may proceed: from ſundry cauſes.</hi> Doubtleſſe happy might that man be, that could apply either this One cauſe, or theſe ſundry cauſes, to this cauſe we haue in hand. Is this your propoſition, If one cauſe may bring forth ſundry effects, and one effect proceede from ſundrie cauſes, then the Actions or Paſsions reported by me in the Demoniakes were not ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall? It is wonderfull what a man ſhal gaine by diſputing with you. For now haue I learned by your priuiledged propoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Not only theſe actions of our Demoniakes not to bee ſupernatural, but alſo neither any action of any Demoniake that either the Apoſtles, or Chriſt himſelfe deliuered. Thirdly, <hi>The like effects iſſue from diuers diſeaſes.</hi> I anſwere, If your skill in phyſicke be ſo great, tell vs, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, from what diſeaſe ſo many &amp; ſtrange effects might ariſe, as are witneſſed to haue bene in theſe parties: &amp; what diſeaſe it was they had? Whether had they the <hi>Lunacie,</hi> or the <hi>phrenſie,</hi> or the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſie,</hi> or the <hi>Mother,</hi> or it was ſome <hi>Convulſions,</hi> or <hi>Crampe</hi> that they had? Name the diſeaſe. And if ſo manie effects doe not proceede from one diſeaſe, as it is very likely, declare how manie diſeaſes they had, and what they were. And whether they had all the diſeaſes you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9803:9"/>
mention: their <hi>ſwelling</hi> ariſing from the <hi>Mother:</hi> their foming from the <hi>Epilepſie,</hi> their extraordinarie ſtrength from <hi>mania,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo had a compounded diſeaſe, percaſe of as manie ſeueral diſeaſes, as they had ſeueral effects. Tel vs alſo whether you haue ſeene one partie afflicted at the ſame time with <hi>Melancholy, Lunacie, Phrenſy, Epilepſy, Mother, Convulſion,</hi> and the <hi>Crampe?</hi> Beſides, whether you haue known ſuch an one, diſeaſed with all theſe grieuous maladies, reſtored againe naturally to his health in one day? When you haue reſolued theſe doubts, we wil hold our ſelues ſatisfied for this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In the meane ſeaſon it remaines for all your anſwere, in as ful force as euer it did. And here we may obſerue, how all that they prattle both here and elſe where of <hi>diſeaſes</hi> (whereby they woulde perſwade, that the paſsions of the Demoniaks were not ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, but might wel proceed from ſome natural diſeaſe) themſelues do ouerthrow, in affirming they are <hi>Counterſeits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, I ſhewing that <hi>The toyes and fooleries, and blasphemous speeches vttered by the parties in their ſupernaturall paſsions, could not come immediately from God, and good Angels, and therefore no doubt from the diuell:</hi> You anſwer firſt, <hi>They were not ſupernaturall effects:</hi> but this is your Cuckow ſong, oft auouched, neuer proued with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie reaſon that might ſo much as beſeeme <hi>William Sommers,</hi> one too renowmed in his time. Secondly, that <hi>this ſuppoſed impoſsibilitie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</note>
               <hi>for either God, or good Angels to effect any ſuch fantaſticall, vaine, and filthy effects, is too groſſe and abſurd.</hi> Indeed you are the Maiſters of abſurdities, you may beſtow one where you wil, as this is a notable one and not to be named, that one ſhould imagine <hi>the moſt Holy Lord, and his holy Angels ſhould immediately by themſelues worke fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy effects.</hi> The blaſphemies which ariſe from hence are not to bee remembred. There is neuer any filthineſſe committed, but either by the filthineſſe of our corrupt fleſh, or by the working of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirits: farre be it from vs, we ſhould once let it enter into our thoughts, that it did firſt iſſue, either from the fountaine, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtreames of puritie. <hi>The Lord his iudgements are tied to a ſeemely maner of effecting,</hi> rightly vnderſtood, which you denie: that is, that all his iudgements ſhould bee effected by meanes beſt beſeeming their nature: as iudgements of committing ſinne are wrought by ſinfull meanes, the Diuel, and wicked men, and ſuch like, and not immediately by holy meanes: for this was to confound light and darkeneſſe, holineſſe and ſinne together. It is lamentable that anie carrying the name of Miniſters amongſt vs, ſhould be ſo impiouſly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9803:10"/>
blind: and yet more lamentable, that they which will ſit at the helme, wil ſuffer ſuch impieties to be offered with their authoritie, to the world. Thirdly you anſwere, That <hi>theſe vncleane effectes do no more argue an vncleane spirit, then thoſe holy effects, as Confeſsing of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 4.</note>
               <hi>Chriſt, and Expounding the Creed argue an holy ſpirit.</hi> As if you had cleane forgotten, <hi>The diuell can transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light.</hi> If you had remembred this, and your old croſſe-row, That there is no reaſoning from contraries in common attributes, you would neuer haue bewrayed ſuch intolerable babiſhneſſe. Laſtly, ſay you, <hi>All this inferres noreall inherency, becauſe the diuel can worke greater matters then theſe remaining without:</hi> concerning which, wee <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. 16.</note>wil ſee (God willing) in that which followeth.</p>
            <p>Againe, wheras is vrged, the Diuels <hi>entring in, &amp; going out</hi> of the partie poſſeſſed, you anſwere, <hi>All theſe speeches, and whatſoeuer text can poſsibly be alleaged throughout the whole Scriptures, concerning ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angels, or Spirits, or Diuels are to be taken metaphorically:</hi> and for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 43 <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 5. 8.</note>this purpoſe you bring <hi>the diuels compaſsing the earth: his walking through drie places: and his roaring like a Lyon.</hi> As if becauſe in theſe places there is ſome Metaphor, therefore all other muſt bee meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical too. Nay then let vs conclude, becauſe theſe texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture be metaphorical, therefore all the Scripture is metaphoricall, and not onely thoſe mentioning Angels and Diuels. And ſo we ſhal reuiue the wickedneſſe of the <hi>Libertines,</hi> of the <hi>Family of loue,</hi> and of the <hi>Suenckefeldians,</hi> acknowledging no literal ſence of the Scripture, but a figuratiue meaning inſpired into themſelues, which only with them is the word of God. VVhen you diſputed of the <hi>Serpent in Euahs tentation,</hi> you contended indeed <hi>The Serpent was onely meant figuratiuely,</hi> yet ſeemed after to reiect this opinion, and I liked well of it. But I crie you mercie: now I vnderſtand you more fully. Wel then, the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> came to <hi>Marie,</hi> and brought tidings of her <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 12. &amp;c. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21. 43.</note>conceiuing the Sonne of God, was this done <hi>Metaphorically?</hi> Was there alſo no ſuch thing literally done, as is reported the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſpake to <hi>Zachary,</hi> concerning <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, whom hee ſhould beget? Was that in figure too, that the Angels comforted our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 22.</note>before his paſsion? Belike when the Diuel caſt the child ſome time into the fire, ſometimes into the water, there was no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 5. 7.</note>indeed, but onely by way of <hi>Metapher.</hi> And when the Diuel cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>VVhat haue I to do with thee O Ieſus the Sonne of the moſt high God,</hi> this voice was <hi>Metaphoricall.</hi> Howſoeuer theſe and many like Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are canonized by you to bee <hi>Metaphoricall,</hi> yet your ſelues
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9803:10"/>
               <hi>Metaphor,</hi> are moſt properly a couple of the abſurdeſt Dunſes that euer put pen to paper. You goe on, and labour to ouerthrow the literall entring of the Diuel, becauſe in <hi>Marke</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>There was a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 17. 1 19. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. 23.</note>
               <hi>man in the Synagogue in an vncleane spirit.</hi> If the words (ſay you bee <hi>taken literally, then the man was eſſentially inherent within the diuell.</hi> I anſwere, Neither are theſe wordes taken literally, neither for this cauſe is the entring of Satan, mentioned elſe where, to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood figuratiuely. The ſame thing may bee, and is vttered ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by figure, and ſometimes by proper ſpeech. One while our Sauiour Chriſt cals himſelfe <hi>The way,</hi> and a <hi>Doore:</hi> In another place he ſaith, That they <hi>which beleeue in him ſhall not periſh,</hi> expounding in plaine tearmes that which is ſpoken by ſimilitude elſe where. As for this Scripture, <hi>To be in an vnclean ſpirit,</hi> is not, as a thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in a thing containing, as water in a veſſell, and ſuch like, but to be in the power of an vncleane ſpirit, as our vulgar tongue expreſſeth fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when we ſay, Such an one is in a Feuer. M. <hi>Beza,</hi> in opening the meaning of this ſpeech, vſeth this ſelfe ſame example: and you your ſelues call it, <hi>A very apt reſemblance.</hi> Seing therefore it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſo wel, let me demaund of you, when we ſay, <hi>A man is in a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> whether you thinke the feuer is within, or without him? You had thought to haue played you with this feuer, but it ſhaketh you a little better then you were aware of. For it plainely declareth, that the natural meaning of the wordes, notwithſtanding they bee figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue, doth note vnto vs an inbeing of the ſpirit. But you adde out <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 20. <hi>Luc.</hi> 4. 33.</note>of Saint Luke: <hi>There was a man in the Synagogues which had a ſpirit of an vncleane diuell. This tranſlations</hi> ſay you, <hi>is tolerable, if by the word Spirit we vnderſtand not the ſimple eſſence, but onely the impulſion, motion, or inspiration of the spirit.</hi> I anſwer, we may, I graunt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the word <hi>spirits</hi> an <hi>impulſions motion,</hi> or <hi>inſpiration,</hi> ſo wee doe not ſeparate this Impulſion and motion from the reall preſence of the Spirit. As when we talke of the vnderſtanding of a man, wee know that vnderſtanding is one thing, and the Man another, yet do not ſeparate betweene the reall preſence of theſe two, but ioyne them together. And to this effect <hi>Caluin</hi> writeth on this place: <hi>This ſpeech</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is as much as if Luke had ſaid, This man was moued by the inſpiration of the diuell: for by God his permiſsion Satan had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed the powers of his ſoule, that he might enforce him at his pleaſure, as wel to speake, as to other motions. And therfore when Demomakes ſpeak, thoſe very diuels, to whoſe rule they are permitted, both ſpeake in them, &amp; by them.</hi> Caluin then graunts an <hi>Inſpiration,</hi> but ioyned with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9803:11"/>
               <hi>preſence:</hi> Theſe men make a diuorce betweene <hi>Inſpiration</hi> and <hi>preſence,</hi> as if theſe two could not abide within ſight one of another. <hi>The inſpiration of the diuell is within, therefore his Eſſence is not:</hi> which is as much to ſay, Becauſe a mans braines be in his head, therefore his wit is in his heeles. But to let this paſſe, this onely I ſay to you, which by <hi>Spirit</hi> here vnderſtand only the <hi>motion, inſpiration, or insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the ſpirit,</hi> and affirme, it is <hi>groſſe to vnderſtand ſpirit Eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> that by this your goodly expoſition, this man muſt bee diſpoſſeſt of a <hi>motion,</hi> and not of a diuell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 21.</note> Further I alleadging, The <hi>Diuell cannot</hi> poſſibly <hi>ſo moue the mem bers of a man as he doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly of demoniaks being only without him, you oppoſe the captiuating of the wicked, his tranſporting of Chriſt, his dispoſing of the tongues of Shimei &amp; Rabſhakeh, his filling of Ananias his heart,</hi> and ſuch like. None of al which makes to any purpoſe. The members of demoniakes are in their ſupernaturall motions moued by the nerues, by the muſcles, by the Tendons, the vſuall mouers of the body: and yet without commaund either of <hi>Will,</hi> or <hi>Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> theſe faculties at that inſtant being diſabled to make choice of things according to their nature: yea ſomtimes there is a moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the body, without the ſeruice of the mouing inſtruments at all. But in the motions by you alleaged, there is no ſuch matter. For in Suggeſtions the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uell by deceiuing the phantaſie, and blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the vnderſtanding, preuaileth againſt the will, and this ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced commanundeth all the inferiour parts, which he may performe outwardly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And as for tranſporting of bodies, here the whole body is caried violently, not by ordinarie ſtirring of thoſe inward moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers appointed to this dutie, but at the pleaſure of an outwarde cauſes as when a man is caried in a ſhip, in a charret<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on horſebacke, or after ſuch other manner. By which it is apparant, the motions which be vſually in Demoniakes, cannot be by outward ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but only by inward operation, as diſpoſing of the ſeuerall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body without the Imagination and VVill, ſometimes by the inſtruments of motion, and ſometimes (which is more <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. 3 &amp; 12. 43. <hi>Mar.</hi> 5. 12.</note>ſtrange) without. Moreouer, I ſhewing ſome argument for his inherencie, from <hi>his earneſt deſire to enter into the bodies of men, and to dwell there:</hi> which appeareth by this, that he is vnwilling to be caſt out: and being throwne out; findeth no reſt till he recouer his loſt habitation: yea he rather deſireth to enter into ſwine then to want a dwelling. You anſwere, <hi>It is an idle conceit to dreame of ſuch a deſire: becauſe, The Lord neuer graunted him, nor hee euer deſired any ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9803:11"/>
thing againſt Iob, &amp; yet no doubt he craued as much againſt him, &amp; had as much yeelded, as euer againſt any.</hi> I reply: Whileſt we are diſputing of the qualitie of the Diuels vexation, you tel vs a tale of the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. We are not now weighing whether <hi>Iob</hi> or Demoniaks are more grieuouſly afflicted, but whether they bee moleſted after the ſame maner. Albeit this is great ignorance in you, to think the torments of the body to proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greater tyranny, then his malice that he powreth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule. Was not his power greater in <hi>Iudas,</hi> though no Demoniake, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the man, whom he had poſſeſſed <hi>a long time?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 5. 3. &amp;c.</note>But to returne to <hi>Iob:</hi> we neuer heard till this day that hee was a Demoniake: and by your rule, if <hi>Iob</hi> was not one (as his booke ſhewes he was not) there was neuer anie: <hi>becauſe as much power was graunted againſt him, as against any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and ſo all thoſe Demoniakes mentioned in the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by your reckening ſhall proue but tales. Let the ſame anſwere ſuffice you for <hi>Ahabs prophets,</hi> vntill wee may heare you are either of a better minde, or of more learning. That which you diſpute of <hi>Saul being poſſeſſed,</hi> is an idle excurſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 29. 30.</note>of your owne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I no where maintaine it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et where you contend that <hi>there were no poſſeſsions at all in Iſrael<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till a little before the comming of Christ,</hi> one might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtly demaund of you, which profeſſe ſo greate inſight in this matter, how the Iewes became ſo cunning to iudge of their poſſeſſed? And why <hi>Eleazarus</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Vespaſian &amp; Ioſephus,</hi> boaſted of <hi>Salomons Exorciſmes?</hi> I doubt not but it was moſt falſe to attribute any ſuch wickednes to that wiſe king: yet theſe men being but a little after our Sauiour Chriſt, might haue beene conuicted by the teſtimonie of many liuing, but eſpecially by their owne hiſtories, if they ſhould haue fathered ſuch practiſes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Salomon,</hi> which had beene euident did begin but yeſterday. It ſeemeth then by opinion of thoſe ancient Iewes, that Poſſeſsions &amp; Diſpoſſeſsions were before <hi>Salomons</hi> time, otherwiſe they would not haue made him an author of a thing that ſprung vp after him. But you will proue by argument, that <hi>none were poſſeſt till a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of Chriſt.</hi> The firſt of your reaſons are contained in theſe words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Thus then it is euident that Saul was neuer poſſeſt, and ſo conſequently, that (till a little before the comming of Christ) there were no poſſeſsions at all in Iſrael.</hi> This argument I anſwere by the like. It is euident that <hi>Saul</hi> had not the <note n="*" place="margin">whiles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee was king.</note>leproſie, <hi>Ergo,</hi> there were no Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in Iſrael, till a little before the comming of Chriſt. The other reaſon you render hereof is, becauſe <hi>this iudgement is not foretold &amp; threatened the Iewes by ſome of the Prophets at leaſt.</hi> As though euerie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9803:12"/>
               <hi>iudgement</hi> of God were ſpecified by ſome of the Prophets. But I <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ag.</hi> 31.</note>wil leaue you to ſport a while with <hi>Saul,</hi> as alſo with that of the <hi>bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen-Serpent,</hi> which is a deuiſe of your owne in this matter, nothing pertaining to me.</p>
            <p>Concerning ſupernaturall effects in <hi>Sommers,</hi> as that <hi>hauing pins</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ag.</hi> 34. &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>thruſt very deepe into his legs and other parts of his body without ſenſe, or feeling thereof Phyſialogus</hi> anſwers, that <hi>Sommers hath ſince depoſed, he felt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes, but diſſembled the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es.</hi> I anſwere, his depoſition no doubt is a thing much to be regarded, which hath ſold himſelfe to be at the Biſhops pleaſure, whereby there was nothing ſo apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe, which he would not dare to affirme, or deny, as hee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his liking. But <hi>Phyſialogus</hi> tels vs further out of <hi>Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> that <hi>the common ſence being earnestly emploied in ſome matter, the outward ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not their owne obiect</hi> whereby <hi>Sommers</hi> in like manner might be ſenſleſſe then, as <hi>Phyſialogus</hi> is now. But to waken him a little, I would he would trie the pinnes himſelfe. No doubt his own meditations being farre more ſerious and waightie, then could bee in that paltrie boy, he ſhould receive no paine at al: of which if we were once aſſured by his experience then were we through for this point. For his <hi>foming, Phyſialogus</hi> anſwers, that <hi>parties affected with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 36.</note>
               <hi>the Epile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſie, foame,</hi> and that <hi>Scoulds do frame:</hi> vnto which adde theſe two Anſwerers: That <hi>foame</hi> out alſo their owne ſhame. Concerning their <hi>violent motions and ſtirrings, extraordinary ſtrength, &amp; knowledge,</hi> you obiect nothing, but what <hi>M. Harſnet</hi> hath done before: vnto whom I haue anſwered. It had beene more be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeming to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to that, then thus to roll ouer the ſame ſtone againe. You call for <hi>Knapping of yron chaines aſunder, and then you would beleeue:</hi> as if the Lord muſt giue power to Satan to feede our vaine humours. But you remember who promiſed to beleeue too, if their curious deſires might haue beene ſatisfied, who euer ſcorned the preſent workes they ſaw, and ſtill deſired greater, but obtained not. If there had beene chaines broken, <hi>M. Harſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> woulde haue charged the Smith with confederacie, and would haue required they had beene <note place="margin">Diſcouery pag. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note>ſo <hi>fastened, as the Keeper of Nemgate could haue faſtened them.</hi> And yet ſuppoſe he had faſtened them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it would haue beene ſaid hee had combined, with vs. If this could be cleared, then <hi>Darrell</hi> ſhould haue bewitched him, or <hi>Sommers</hi> himſelfe ſhoulde bee a witch. If this would not ſerue yet ſome by argument would maintaine, that none can be poſſeſſed in theſe dayes: nay, that there were neuer any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed. So be the matter neuer ſo true and impoſsible to be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9803:12"/>
ſome thing would euer be excepted, as long as wee haue to deale with men Lords ouer their owne tongues, and haue no Lord on earth to controll them. Conſidering then I haue to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with men of this kind, who, ſo they bee ſaying ſomething, ſpare not to ſay any thing bee it neuer ſo falſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vncredible, and abſurd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it ſhall be folly in me to ſpend words about them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 41.</note> You affirme: <hi>The Deponents themſelues haue ſince more adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed their oaths and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſed the contrary.</hi> I anſwer: They haue done nothing leſſe. Nay their reexaminations make more for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, then weakening of that they formerly depoſed. And this I haue made euident in my former anſwere to the Chapter of <hi>Reex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Detect lib. <hi>3</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>where <hi>M. Harſnet</hi> obiecteth the very ſame you do here. VVhereunto you ſhould haue returned a reply, or elſe for ſhame neuer mentioned that, which is already anſwered. But you may bee aſhamed (if you be not paſt all ſhame) to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they reexamined depoſed thus: namely, that <hi>now by their better enlightened iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, they plainly perceiue all thoſe the former ſuppoſed ſupernaturall actions or paſsions, to be but meere counterfeit toyes, and plaine coſoning practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> O palpable flaunder! What wil you ſticke to affirme, who ſpare not to publiſh this for truth? I refer thee good Reader, to my <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>the place before quoted, where thou ſhalt ſee this to be moſt vntrue Whereas, I ſay, <hi>they would haue puniſhed the witneſſes, if theſe things had beene found counterfeit:</hi> you anſwere, as if they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed vpon compaſsion, being ſilly poore perſons: and yet of about thirtie that haue teſtified the things vnpoſsible to be counterfeited, vpon their corporali oathes, ſeuen of them be preachers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 43. &amp;c.</note> After you come to the <hi>ſignes of Poſſeſſions</hi> which you denie <hi>to bee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſet downe as rules to diſcerne Eſſentiall Poſſeſſions by.</hi> They be rules of ſuch poſſeſsions as were in the Scriptures and wee haue ſhewed them to be Eſſentiall, whatſoeuer yet you either haue, or can prate to the contrarie. How fooliſh and beggarly the words be, you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther multiply to this end, I haue manifeſted in your Diſcourſes, I need not repeate them. For the <hi>number of ſignes</hi> I ſtand not ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon them. Where they are all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſay there is a Poſſeſſion: I doe not ſay, where there be fewer, or diuers others, there is no Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For this is free to the Lord to afflict in what meaſure it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him. Neither do I <hi>croſſe my ſelfe,</hi> as you vntruly charge me, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag</hi> 45.</note>
               <hi>the Scripture ſignes the onely meanes to diſcerne of Poſſeſsions: and then in the</hi> 16. &amp; 17. <hi>pag. euery way equal my experimented ſignes with any of them.</hi> I onely in the pages mentioned name ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewe ſuper
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9803:13"/>
naturall effects, which in experience I haue obſerued in Domoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akes. But in what place I ſet them, and how I account of them, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident in the 37. page, where ſpeaking of experimented ſignes, I vſe theſe words: <hi>But the Scripture making no mention of theſe ſignes, they are to be regarded accordingly.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o likewiſe in the 22. page. In <hi>the applicaion of the ſignes,</hi> you impute vnto me diuers contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g</hi> 46.</note>after your lying and ſlaunderous manner. As if I ſhould ſay: <hi>Sometimes they haue ſupernatural ſtrength and knowledge, yet ſometimes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctr. pag.</hi> 6. 17.</note>
               <hi>againe, they onely ſeeme to haue. Sometime Satan hurtes, but hurtes not indeed,</hi> &amp;c. Touching the firſt of theſe, I hauing ſpoken of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall ſtrength and knowledge of the parties controuerted, in the concluſion thereof ſhew, that I <hi>am not ſo to be vnderſtood, as though I meant that they had ſupernaturall ſtrength and knowledge: but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this aſcribed vnto them by mee, becauſe they ſeeme to haue ſuch knowledge and ſtrength.</hi> And thus oft in ſcripture is that attributed to Demoniakes, which was indeed perfourmed by the diuell, and done onely by them in a ſeeming ſhew. So the Demoniake, <hi>Mark</hi> 5. is ſaid to <hi>breake chaines and fetters aſunder,</hi> whereas not he, but the diuell brake them. And this is one of your worthy contradictions. Concerning the latter, I ſay thus, that <hi>Howſoever they are ſo miſerably vexed by Satan, as the behold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s would iudge them in moſt extreme and intollerable paines, yet they feele no paines at all. Yet</hi> I <hi>doubt not but that Satan can jo order the matter, as that the Poſſeſſed ſhall haue paine, when he ſhall ſee it ſerue for his purpoſe,</hi> &amp;c. By which I ſhewe there is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 48.</note>not one vniforme order to be expected in theſe caſes: which varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of affliction, theſe men would draw to inconſtancie of opinion. You condemne me alſo for <hi>thinking, The Scripture ſignes are not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corded onely as matter of fact, but partly to helpe vs in diſcorning of poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſsions.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 21.</note>I ground my reaſon on the queſtion of our Sauiour: <hi>How long time is it he hath beene thus?</hi> You anſwere, <hi>Chriſt respecteth in this question onely the firſt time of that accident.</hi> And I reply, you reſpect in this anſwer how to trifle off any thing ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected againſt you, with fooliſh words without any ſubſtance at all. Doth not our Sauiour loyne together with the time, the maner and forme of his handling? Doth he not enquire as well of the one, as of the other? We muſt haue a queſtion of time without any ſubiect matter, or reference to any thing. Miraculous Anſwerers, which can meaſure time without any ſtandard laid vnto it! You charge me with <hi>foiſting in words into the text</hi> for aduantage: but it is your owne mouthes which runne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 49.</note>ouer with the word <hi>Eſſentially,</hi> and not any addition of mine. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="tcp:9803:13"/>
my ſelfe with the phraſe of the holy Ghoſt, reiecting theſe tearmes as needleſſe and ſuperfluous. Though whereſoeuer the diuel is, this ſpeech properly vnderſtood (as it is vſually in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Poſſeſsion) there muſt alſo his ſpiritual eſſence be. That which you thinke is more then the text, is onely added to paraphraſe it: and though theſe words <hi>In him,</hi> be not in this Scripture, yet are they elſe where vſed in like caſe: you are very hungry, which would leap <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19, 1</note>at ſo ſmall a morſell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether there be a medicine or no for curing Eſsentiall poſſeſsion,</hi> you yay, <hi>we ſhall ſee after in handl ng that joint.</hi> and I am content to refer <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag</hi> 50. 51 52.</note>it thither. As for <hi>speedie deliuer a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee of the afflicted,</hi> I acknowledge it is no argument of poſſeſsion: and I thanke you for reprouing it, though of my ſelfe I would be ready to retract anie thing diſſonant from the truth. It is not my deſire, any my ſtubble ſhould bee layd vpon the foundation, but I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent the fire of Gods word ſhould conſume it.</p>
            <p>I alleaging thoſe words of the law, <hi>That the Lord will bring vpon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 6 <hi>pag.</hi> 53. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uel.</hi> 22. 1</note>
               <hi>tranſgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, and euery plague which is not written in the booke of the Law, vntill they be deſtroyed.</hi> And alſo that of Saint <hi>Iohn: He that ſhall adde vnto theſe things, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagues that are written in this booke,</hi> to proue that men may now be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: you anſwere, <hi>I abuſe the Scripture, making Poſſeſsion ſametimes written, ſometimes vnwritten.</hi> But you abuſe your ſelues, and your Reader to iangle about that, which euerie childe might teach you. For who knowes not that ſome thinges might bee vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Law, that be very frequent in the Goſpel, as indeed Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion is? But to anſwer my argument out of theſe places, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 53.</note>
               <hi>Eſſentiall poſſeſsion to be decrced in God his eternall counſell for a iudgement.</hi> That Poſſeſsion is <hi>eſsentiall,</hi> we haue ſufficiently proued in ſuruey of your <hi>Diſcourſes.</hi> That it is <hi>decreed for a iudgement,</hi> may appeare to any not wilfully blind, by thoſe manifolde examples of men poſſeſſed in the Scriptures: Except thoſe things hapned beſide the decree of God, or elſe thoſe poſſeſsions were rewards and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, not iudgements and afflictions It may be your impudent vaine will not ſticke to admit either<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though none can avouch the firſt but Atheiſts, nor the ſecond but only men that are mad. I haue ſhewed in your <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> how the Lords iudgements are perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, though not inflicted euerie moment, but after ſuch intermiſsion as pleaſeth him. Is it not then excellent ſtuffe you bring, <hi>That the iudgements of this life</hi> (for we ſpeake only of them) <hi>cannot perpetually <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 54.</note>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9803:14"/>
bee inflicted, but ſalvation must needs be barred from all in Chriſt?</hi> In like maner, becauſe I ſay, <hi>Poſſeſsion is but a conditionall and temporall iudgement,</hi> you therefore interre, <hi>It is not perpetuall.</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere you play with the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meaning <hi>perpetuall,</hi> a continued connexion, ſuch as nothing may be put betweene, when as that is vſually ſaid to bee perpetuall, which is common to all ages, though it appeare but now <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 55.</note>and then. You charge me with diſputing from <hi>May be,</hi> to <hi>a being in deed.</hi> May not I wel diſpute, <hi>It may be,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you would euerie where maintaine <hi>It cannot bee?</hi> How can a being indeede bee concluded, before it be manifeſt the ſame thing <hi>May be?</hi> If the heauens there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fall, we ſhall not onely catch Larks, as you ſay, but by catching alſo of you two, we ſhall catch ſomething that wants braines.</p>
            <p>I affirming, <hi>There is as great cauſe of this iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t now, as at any time heretofore:</hi> you anſwere, It <hi>is v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rly vntrue: The manifeſtation of Chriſts Deitie, and the confirmation of his glorious Goſpel being the maine cauſes of poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſts time.</hi> My meaning is as appeareth by my words, there is as great cauſe in reſpect of ſin, as much abounding now as euer. For I do not compare this cauſe of puniſhment, with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Chriſt his Deitie. And therfore beſides the ceaſing of the two <hi>maine cauſes,</hi> you ſhould alſo haue ſhewed that ſin was cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or elſe ſinne to be no cauſe: which you purpoſe to doe in the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 56.</note>pages following. But in the meane ſeaſon, how doe you flouriſh it, as if I ſhould proudly <hi>limit the Lord his times and ſeaſons for inflicting his iudgements?</hi> I limit no times, but leaue it free to the Lord: yet knowing the reward of ſinne, and the ample kingdom it now hath, according to the maner of all the Prophets, I can do no leſſe then expect his fearefull iudgements of what kind ſo euer. But you will <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 57. 58.</note>proue <hi>Poſſeſsion is no puniſhment for ſinne,</hi> and that out of the <hi>Depth of Divinity.</hi> Your reaſon is, <hi>Afflictions of this life, laid vpon the Elect, be not properly puniſhments.</hi> It is true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but what do you lay to this? <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſsion of Diuels is an affliction of this life.</hi> We graunt this too: yet ſo, that not onely Poſſeſsion is an affliction of this life, but that there be infinite other miſeries and calamities beſides. What then? Shall we now conclude, That no miſerie or calamitie whatſoeuer, as well as this of Poſſeſsion, is any puniſhment for ſinne? O deepe Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and ſuch as hath not beene raiſed from the bottomleſſe pit till now! I denie not but the Lord may impoſe it vpon a man for trial, and for other ends, as he knowes beſt, but may he not alſo therfore inflict it as a chaſtiſement for ſinne, or caſtigatorie puniſhment? But your aſſumption containeth more in it, vz. that <hi>Poſſeſsion is an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9803:14"/>
of this life laid vpon the elect.</hi> This alſo I conſeſſe is true: but it will not aduantage you, except ye adde, that it is <hi>laid onely vpon the elect,</hi> and then ſhall we haue Poſſeſsion a note of our election, and ſo a bleſſed thing to be poſſeſt with diuels, which is ſuch diuinitie, as neuer Diuine, deepe or ſhallow, once dreamed of. It is a ſhame to rehearſe your fooleries. Then you will vrge it more ſtrongly, for that our <hi>Sauiour curing the poſſeſſed hath giuen them no watchword of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 14.</note>
               <hi>ſinning no more.</hi> I his <hi>watchw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> was giuen but in one cure, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Was all other diſeaſes therefore no chaſtiſements for ſin? Whether our Sauior ſpeake, or whether be ſilent, you are men that can take occaſion for your abſurdities vpon either. I will not waſte paper with rehearſing more of this ſtuffe. Conſider with your ſelues <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2, 12 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.</note>that leſſer affli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions be puniſhments for ſinne, as we ſpeake vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if your profunditie will giue vs leaue: That all death is the ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of ſinne, and that Poſſeſsion is a kind of death. Beſides, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders are deliuered to Satan by the Church, not for reward, but for Chaſtiſement. And if to bee in the power of Satan howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, bee a chaſtiſement, what is it to be in his poſſeſsion? Is not he the Executioner appointed ouer the wicked? Hath not hee the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14 1. 2. 44</note>power of death? How can any one be in his hands, and bee not in death? Or how in death, and not in puniſhment? Our Sauiour teacheth that Repoſſeſsion hapneth vpon negligence and ſecuritie, whereby it may bee apparant, that the firſt poſſeſsion is not for a mans vertues. It it needleſſe to vſe many prooffes in a plaine caſe, if I had not to deale with men to whom Sunſhine is darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>teſtimonies of the Doctors,</hi> which I alleage <hi>in the Margine,</hi> you <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 59.</note>blame, for that <hi>they be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ully ſet downe.</hi> You haue examined them in your <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> and confeſſe they ſpeake as I report them. I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <note place="margin">Dialog. Diſc. pag. <hi>171.</hi>
               </note>in this place to put downe their wordes, being after to vſe them in proofe of Diſpoſſeſsion by prayer and faſting ſince mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ceaſed. Which poſition you ſee includes the former, and to what purpoſe ſhould I clogge the Reader with vnneceſſarie repetition? Nay what ſhould I be burdenſome to you? For in that place where they do ſpeake, they ſpeake ſo plainely, as you could wiſh their tongues were out, as we ſhal ſee in the next dialogue. If you would diſcredite <hi>VVierus,</hi> reporting <hi>ſeuentie damſels in Rome poſſeſſed with ſpirits in one night,</hi> it had beene meet you ſhould haue done it with ſome probabilitie: It is not ynough, for that it was at <hi>Rome.</hi> VVill you credit nothing done in that kingdome? No maruell, you will not credit things done at home, though neuer ſo ſubſtantially cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9803:15"/>
It is likely, if it had bene but a practiſe of <hi>Romane Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rciſts,</hi> they would haue diſpatched it in leſſe then <hi>two yeares.</hi> None of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was recouered within this time. To haue ſo many poſſeſſed, and for ſo long time, and not one of them to be diſpoſſeſſed, made little for the credit of the Exorciſts, and of the Popiſh Church, if Diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be a marke of the true Church, as the Papiſts teach. And ſo of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1566</note>the <hi>thirtie children poſſeſſed at Amſterdam,</hi> the ſame yeare they broke downe their images, and reformed the Religion, as if the Diuell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more raged, conſidering his ſhort time there, as he vſually doth at his farewell. <hi>Thyreus</hi> his report may be allowed at leaſt, in thinges <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ag.</hi> 60.</note>that are witneſſed by others. Neither did <hi>D. Fulke not inveigh againſt Poſſeſsi n, becauſe it had no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>intainers to his time,</hi> but becauſe it was gainſaid by none. <hi>M. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, M La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, M. Robinſon,</hi> with ſundry other Diuines liuing in <hi>D. Fulk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his time were of opinion there were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions, as appeared by their pra tiſe, and ſome of their writings. But what needed any ſhould with earneſtnes defend that, which no man of any reckening oppagned? This controuerſie is new ſprung vp, firſt hatched, and brought into light by enuie, and ſtill nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by flatterie and Ambition, and expertation to get ſomething from his good Lordſhip. For your argument <hi>from Micacles,</hi> I hope I haue quaſhed it in your tenth Dialogue. Is it not wonderfull that you acknowledging <hi>Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſsion to be aſure naturall diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an l a thing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 62.</note>
               <hi>hidden in the ſecret counſel of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, to execute and effect when and where he will, and therefore may neu r by any man liuing be auouched for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> that you dare ſo preſumptuouſly conclude, that <hi>now there can be nop ſſ ſsion?</hi> If it be ſo <hi>ſecret</hi> as you ſay, it is no leſſe daunger for you to denie it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then for me to affirme it. But you are like the prudent topper of trees, that ſtrikes in ſunder the verie bough hee ſtands on.</p>
            <p>For <hi>prayer and fasting how it is a meanes to expell Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an,</hi> wee ſhall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 62. 63.</note>ſee more, God willing in the next Dialogue, if any thing bee need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be added to that already ſpoken. VVhereas I put a difference between the curing of poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s now, &amp; thoſe done by the Apoſtles for that now it is done by an <hi>intreating word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> then <hi>by a base co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding word.</hi> you anſwere as beſeemeth your ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urd faſhion, that <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous curing of poſſeſsions in Chriſts time was at n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand effected by a bare c mmaunding word, but by a ſupernaturall power concurring therewith.</hi> O deepe Clerks, and men that haue diued to the verie bottome of Diuinitie! VVhen we make compariſon of meanes v<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſed by men, what haue we to doe with <hi>ſupernaturall power?</hi> Doth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9803:15"/>
eyther the <hi>intreating word</hi> or <hi>Commaunding word</hi> exclude that? Would any men in their wits denie the work of the inſtrument, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is moued by the principall cauſe? Meate doth not nouriſh, becauſe the Lord giueth ſtrength, &amp; the ſtaffe to bread: Faith is not by hearing, becauſe it is the giftof God. Such are the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wherewith theſe <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> think they haue put all the world to ſilence: which happily they haue done, except it be for laughing. I do no where affirme that Poſſeſsion is <hi>a naturall diſeaſe,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 64. <hi>Matt.</hi> 8. 16. 17. <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. 21.</note>do not goe about by <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 24. and <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 21. to proue it, becauſe in thoſe places it is iointly <hi>recorded with naturall diſeaſes,</hi> wherewith you charge me, and by diuerſe arguments verie ſoberly confute me: but ſaying that <hi>Poſſeſsion with Diuels is in the Gospel oft brought in among other plagues of God,</hi> for proofe thereof, I doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the aforeſaid Scriptures. Indeed I ſay, that <hi>Poſſoſsion is a diſeaſe,</hi> but adde, <hi>to wit, ſupernaturall:</hi> and a little after call it an <hi>vnnaturall diſcaſe:</hi> VVhereby I make it plaine, what manner of diſeaſe I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it to be. If you would nowe haue confuted me, you ſhould haue bent your force againſt theſe things I ſay, and not againſt that I no where do affirme. But this is with you an vſuall thing. You adde, that I <hi>deeming poſſeſsion to be but a meere naturall maladie, doe directly croſſe my former speech, where I make it a ſupernaturall mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</hi> And this forſooth is one of your Contradictions. But you muſt firſt proue better then you haue done yet, that I doe not onely <hi>deeme,</hi> but ſay, that <hi>Poſſeſsion is a naturall maladie,</hi> before it be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that <hi>I croſſe mine owne speech.</hi> If I were giuen as much to croſſe my body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as you ſay I am to <hi>croſſe my ſelfe in my ſpeech,</hi> I were a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fit man to make a Papiſt, who loue of life to <hi>croſſe</hi> themſelues. To make vp your ſumme, you foiſt vs in a counterfeit, That <hi>all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 65.</note>
               <hi>works are miracles,</hi> as if faith, hope, and charitie, peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and ſuch like were all miracles: which if it be true, we muſt needs ſtil haue miracles, or els haue no Church. The Papiſts would be glad to heare of theſe tidings, but no body elſe, except ſuch as would reio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce at your folly. For your <hi>ſecond, third, fourth,</hi> and <hi>fiſt Dialogues, wherein,</hi> you thinke, <hi>you haue ouerthrowne Eſſentiall poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> by that time you haue weighed in a iuſt ballance, what hath beene anſwered thereunto, you ſhall perceiue to haue preuailed as much, as if you had laboured to ouerthrow your Peake hils. You <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 66. 67.</note>ſay, <hi>You haue ſhewed Paſſeſsion is not inflicted for ſinne,</hi> but I ſay, you muſt ſhew it better, before any man of wiſdome can beleeue you. I haue branded your abſurditie in your <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> for that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9803:16"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 12. 31.</note> a <hi>finall end of poſſeſſion from the casting forth of the prince of this world.</hi> Here you increaſe it a thouſand folde in making your owne ſingular, fooliſh, and impious wreſting of this Scripture, to contain a matter of no leſſe certaintie, then is the expreſſe word of God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 9. 14. 15.</note>for an <hi>vtter end of any the like floud to that, which was in Noabs time.</hi> I do not tie the Lord <hi>to the puniſhment of Gomorrah, or of the children deriding the prophet, or of Cehazi,</hi> and ſuch others: but where the like ſinnes raigne, there may be the like puniſhment, which you will not grant in actuall Poſſeſsion, hauing put a neceſſarie end vnto it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But you wil not be preſſed with <hi>May be.</hi> Much a do you keep with this <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 68.</note>Sophiſme, <hi>a poſſe ad eſſe.</hi> Wherfoeuer you meet with <hi>may</hi> or <hi>can</hi> in the concluſion, then eftſoones you tell vs of this fallacie. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in your <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> your skil in Rhetorike, &amp; in diſcerning of <hi>Tropes</hi> did faile you: ſo here it doth in Logicke, &amp; in diſcerning <hi>Elenchs.</hi> To auouch <hi>Poſſ ſſion of d uels to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inflicted alſo for ſinne is Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kolike melodie</hi> in your eares, but you haue ſung vs a Iacke Dawes ſong in limitting it with <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 67.</note>
               <hi>two onely ends,</hi> that is, <hi>of confirmation of Chaiſts Deity, and of the Gospell,</hi> as I haue abundantly proued.</p>
            <p>Whereas I affirme the iudgement of our ſenſes for the truth of <hi>Sommers vexation by Satan,</hi> you reply, <hi>Our ſenſes could not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 69.</note>
               <hi>ſuch ſupernaturall matters:</hi> beſides, <hi>they might be deluded, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels can do things in ſhew.</hi> For <hi>comprehenſion,</hi> ſeeing you depriue vs of all iudgement of ſenſe, blame vs not if we be ſomething dull in conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing this, How that ſeeing, we do not ſee: feeling, we do not feele: ſmelling, we do not ſmell: and hearing, wee doe not heare: and that we require you would make it plaine vnto vs. Which when you haue once done, and beaten into our heads, I will neuer truſt mine eyes againe, though I ſhould ſee <hi>M. Deacon</hi> in forme of an Angel of light. But if our <hi>ſenſes were deluded,</hi> &amp; things <hi>done in ſhew,</hi> that were not in deed, ſurely it was Satan that deluded vs and no counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>Sommers,</hi> as you would faine haue it. This is the ſumme of your firſt dialogue againſt me, to which <hi>Lycanthropus</hi> ſubſcribeth as <hi>able to ſuffice any reaſonable man:</hi> but this, is but a ſmall thing, ſaith <hi>Pueumatomachus,</hi> and therfore he ſtretcheth the matter to an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er pitch, That <hi>neither any vnreaſonable man</hi> (which is much more) <hi>ſhall be euer able to anſwer it.</hi> So that now we are much beholding to M. <hi>Deacon,</hi> and M. <hi>Walker,</hi> that haue put all <hi>fooles</hi> and mad men to a perpetuall <hi>non plus,</hi> whoſe tongues would otherwiſe continually bee tampring.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſtraunge and preſent affliction of the boy of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9803:16"/>
               <hi>Northwitch,</hi> I will ſay nothing: I neuer ſawe him: howſoeuer you deſcant on the matter after your lying &amp; pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry maner. Yet <hi>I</hi> think <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 71.</note>it not amiſſe to offer to thy view (good Reader) the iudgement of the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> in his direction to his parents, and of three other Commiſsioners for cauſes Eccleſiaflicall, according with him therein.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>FIrſt we thinke it fit, and doe require the parents of the ſaid childe, that they ſuffer not any to repaire to their houſe to viſite him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſauing ſuch as are in authority, and other perſons of ſpeciall regard and knowne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and to haue speciall care that the number alwayes be very ſmal. Further hauing ſeene the bodily affliction of the ſaid child, and obſerued in ſundry fits v ry ſtrange effects and operations, either proceeding of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vnknowne cauſes, or of ſome diabolical practiſe: we thinke it conue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nient and fit for the eaſe and deliuerance of the ſaid childe from his grie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous afflictions, that prayer be made for him publikely by the minister of the pariſh, or any other preacher repairing thither, before the congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſo oft as the ſame aſſembleth. And that certaine preachers, namely, <hi>M. Garrad, M. Maſſey, M. Coller, M. Haruey, M. Eaton, M. Pierſon</hi> and <hi>M. Brownhill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> theſe onely and none other to repaire vnto the ſaide child by turnes, as their leiſures will ſerue, and to vſe their diſcretions by priuate prayer and fasting, for the eaſe and comfort of the afflicted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with all requiring them to abstaine from all ſolemne meetings, becauſe the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lamitie is particular, and the authoritie of the allowing and preſcribing ſuch meetings resteth neither in them nor in vs, but in our Superiours, whoſe pleaſure it is fit we ſhould expect. Moreouer, becauſe it is by ſome held that the child is really poſſeſſed of an vncleane ſpirit, for that there appeareth to vs no certaintie, nor yet any great probability thereof, wee thinke it alſo conuenient, and require the preachers aſoreſaid to forbeare all formes of Exorciſme, which alwayes imply and preſuppoſe a reall and actuall poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>Rich. Ceſtrienſis.</item>
                           <item>Dauid Yale. <hi>Chancel.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Griff. Vaughan.</item>
                           <item>Hugh Burghes.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hereunto I will adde a fewe lines, which <hi>M. Haruey</hi> aforeſaid, a man of great learning and godlines, writ in his life time to a friend of his.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Grace &amp; mercie from our only Sauior. There is ſuch a boy as your report
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9803:17"/>
ſignifieth, whoſe eſtate from the beginning of February till this preſent, hath beene ſo ſtrange and extraordinarie, in regard of his paſſions, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and speeches, as I for my part neuer heard, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read of the like. Few that haue ſeene the variety of his fits, but they thinke the diuell hath the dispoſing of his body. My ſelfe haue diuers times ſeene him, and ſuch things in him as are impoſſible to proceed from any humane creature. The matter hath affected our whole countrey. The Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines with vs generally hold, that the child is really poſſeſſed. And ſo much for him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Wee ſee what the Biſhop and Preachers of Cheſſe-ſhire their iudgement is touching this child. What ſay nowe the <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> concerning him? They after they haue for three leaues together ſcofted at his <hi>grieuous affliction</hi> (for ſo the Biſhop before tearmeth it) in moſt prophane, childiſh, and ſcurrulous maner, doe in the end <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 76.</note>affirme, that he counterfeiteth, and that this would ſoone apeare, <hi>if be were well coni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed a while with a three corded whip.</hi> Is this the fruit of your viſiting the child? you had better haue kept you at home. VVas this all the comfort the diſtreſſed boy and parents receiued from you? Miſerable comforters then are you. Is this the mercy, and all the bowels of compaſsion that is in you, towards him that is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 15.</note>in miſerie? O mercileſſe men, and voyd of all pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie! It appeareth you haue not learned to <hi>weepe, with them that weepe.</hi> VVell, I can tell you of a couple of ſuch merrie or mercileſſe companions as your ſelfes, that comming of late to one M. <hi>tames Charles</hi> of Wolroych in Kent, to ſee his daughter <hi>Clemens Charles,</hi> who is reputed to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſt with the diuell, &amp; not without cauſe, they ſcarce went ſo merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly home, as they were at M. <hi>Charles,</hi> and yet but a ſmall thing befell them by the way. Returning home, they went by one M. <hi>Hooke</hi> his houſe of <hi>Darlton,</hi> maiſter not long before to this maid, at whoſe houſe ſhe began to bee afflicted. Now as they were on horſebacke before M. <hi>Hooke</hi> his doore, and ſporting themſelues with him about the counterfeiting of this new vpſtart counterfeit. behold, one of their horſes ſtaled bloud, and as they were talking thereof, loe. the other did the like: whereat they were ſomewhat appaulled. How it fared with their horſes after I know not, but the day following they caried themſelues at M. <hi>Charles</hi> more ſoberly, whether they went on other horſes. But hereof ynough: I will nowe proceede to your ſecond Dialogue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="treatise">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9803:17"/>
            <head>A REPLIE TO THE SECOND DIALOGVE.</head>
            <p>THe ſecond part of my <hi>Doctrine</hi> treateth, That <hi>thoſe eight before mentioned were verily dispoſſeſſed, &amp; that by faſting and prayer, the meanes appointed by God.</hi> For confirmation wherof, I knew no better rule then the example of men diſpoſſeſſed in holy Scripture, which is the onely true and vnſallible touchſtone to examine both this, and all other actions by. Theſe <hi>Anſwerers</hi> ſcorne theſe <hi>notes,</hi> calling <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>them <hi>falſly pretended ſignes of dispoſſeſsion from ſacred Scripture,</hi> and therefore pretermitting them, require my argumentes, as if the Signes from Scripture were no arguments at all. It ſeemeth you haue found a veine of better mettal then the Scriptures, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence your whole booke is ſo full ſtuffed with your owne ſhining droſſe, and is ſo vtterly deſtitute of this purified gold. Yet you cannot beat me from them, but I vrge them thus: <hi>There were in our Demoniakes the ſelfe ſame ſignes or notes of dispoſſeſſion, precedent and ſubſequent, which wee rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of in the Scripture Demoniakes, and therefore the ſame dispoſſeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> you anſwere, <hi>There were not the ſame ſignes in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniakes: and firſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>they were meere coſonages, as is confeſſed freely by the parties themſelues vpon their owne oathes.</hi> I reply, the parties we ſpeake of, bee eight in number, whereof onely <hi>Sommers</hi> hath made this curſed confeſſion: which was not free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, <note place="margin">Detect. pag. <hi>127.</hi>
               </note>as you vntruly affirme, but extorted by Satan, and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as in my <hi>Detection</hi> I haue made manifeſt. But what ſay you to the ſeuen in <hi>Lancaſhire?</hi> It may be <hi>Sommers</hi> hath ſworne for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all: for they as yet, were neuer examined: yet becauſe we doubt of <hi>Somers</hi> general oath, <hi>I</hi> pray you proue vnto vs, who taught the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to counterfeit? when, and where, and by what meanes they were taught? what end might induce them to imbrace ſuch tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? whether the parents were priuy to it? and what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in practiſing ſuch wickedneſſe? Yea, put <hi>Sommers</hi> too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the roll, &amp; ſhew vs what man is able by practiſe to do the things that either <hi>Sommers</hi> or they did? And one woulde thinke a man of meane agility might quickly performe that, which cofoning yong boyes and girles could. Shew vs, I beſeech you, theſe and ſuch like things, or otherwiſe if you cannot ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; yet tel vs of <hi>coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nage,</hi> you ſhew vs nothing but your long eares, &amp; braſen faces. Secondly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9803:18"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi> 83.</note> ſay you, <hi>The ſignes in the Scripture Demoniakes were ſenſibly perc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the beholders: but theſe in your pretended Demoniakes were not ſo, by your own confeſsion.</hi> Belike all we that were ſpectators of our Demoniakes, being (at ſundrie times) a great multitude, were all ſtricken with blindneſſe, with deafneſſe, and with a benummednes, and yet we all thought we vſed our ſenſes, and I am ſure, wee were no ſooner out of the place, but we were able, the Lord bee thanked, to ſee, heare and feele. But you confirme this by <hi>mine own confeſsion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. pag. <hi>37</hi>
               </note>which ſaith, that <hi>the ſpirit could not poſsibly be felt or ſeene.</hi> I ſaid ſo, &amp; ſay ſo againe, that Spirits cannot be felt or ſeene in their owne bare eſſence, but as they make themſelues knowne vnto vs by their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. I angling Sophiſters will diſpute, That the noſe of a mans face cannot be ſeene, becauſe that which we ſee is but colour or forme, and the noſe it ſelfe is neither of both. Your eares ring it may bee with their noiſe, which hath made you borrow an argument from them. Thirdly, you ſay, The <hi>Signes we report are falſe:</hi> which I would graunt you if your ſelues had learned to ſpeake truth. We muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member there are aboue two hundred witneſſes hereof liuing at this day, of which ſome haue depoſed the ſame wee report of <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</hi> Fourthly, ſay you, <hi>Scripture Signes can argue no Dispoſſeſsion now, becauſe like effects may ariſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naturall cauſes, and coporall diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> By this your good helpe Atheiſts might ouerthrow all Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Diſpoſſeſsions in the ſcripture. But howſoeuer you may be friendly to ſuch vile wretches, yet haue they no foothold from hence. For neither thoſe effects in thoſe ancient Demoniakes, nor in theſe of our time iointly &amp; wholy conſidered can proceed from naturall diſeaſe. Naturall cauſes can bring forth no ſupernaturall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as we haue demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrated theſe to be in ſpight of your ſeuenth Dialogue, and what other treaty ſo euer you oppoſe againſt it. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, ſay you, <hi>A diſpoſſeſsion may bee without ſuch apparant ſignes, and therefore your ſignes precedent and ſubſequent do not neceſſarily conclude a dispoſſeſsion.</hi> What? Becauſe it is ſometimes without theſe ſignes, therefore where theſe ſignes are, ſhall it not be? It is ſometime day light without the cleare ſunſhine, therefore when the Sunne ſhines cleare ſhall it not be day? Sometimes the murderer ſlayes a man and is not taken with the manner, therefore if he be taken with the manner, ſhall he not neceſſarily bee concluded a murtherer? Theſe are good rules to make a man impudent in ſinne: for by them the bold offender ſhall ſpeede better, then hee that doth it minchingly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You haue ſpoken then pretily againſt theſe ſignes, but without any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9803:18"/>
ſigne of truth or wit.</p>
            <p>From Scripture ſignes I deſcend to ſome experimented by my ſelfe in dealing with Demoniakes, which haue reported certaine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſhapes, in which the diuels ſeemed to depart from them. But here I am taken vp for halting, in that I call it <hi>My experience, which was proued in the perſons of other.</hi> I confeſſe I ſpake rudely, as all other men do, which call a phyſition a man of good experience, though he hath not proued all the diſeaſes, he hath dealt with, in his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 84.</note>As for <hi>viſible ſhapes, you vtterly deny, that Spirits could procure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> yet they did before <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and infinite others ſince, as wee haue ſhewed by better arguments in my ſuruey of your fourth and fift Dialogues, then you euer haue, or can for the contrarie. Some alſo I ſhew did <hi>vomit,</hi> or ſtraine to vomit when the diuel departed. With <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 85.</note>this you make good ſport, perhaps ticled with remembrance, that you haue returned to your owne vomit.</p>
            <p>Further, I concluding a diſpoſſeſsion, from the preſent effect of our prayers (wherof the like is not in naturall diſeaſes.) You charge me with <hi>proper tearmes, as with certaine charming words to coniure the Lord with,</hi> for ſo it pleaſeth your prophane mouthes to ſpeake. And yet I do not vſe the word <hi>proper.</hi> Onely I ſay, <hi>And God heard our prayer vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red in ſuch tearmes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that is, made to that effect, as before I haue ſhewed in briefe. I neuer dreamed that ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Argooſes would come after mee with ſo manie eyes, to finde an hole in my coate for theſe words more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all other mens. But to let words paſſe, you would diſproue the effect of our prayers, for that we could not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 86.</note>make the parties <hi>the Temples of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> as we had prayed. Wee challenge no ſuch power, but we might well hope of the mercy of the Lord to ſanctifie them, which did plainly behold his great good neſſe in deliuering them from Satans great rage. Howſoeuer mee thinks you ſhould not be offended with vs for putting vp this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to God. And what if the Lord doth not alwayes yeelde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſucceſſe to the prayers of his ſeruants? Could we not therfore be aſſured he had now heard vs, when we ſaw the thing performed before our eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is true the Diuel ſometime ſeemeth to depart, when he doth not but when it is at the requeſts of Gods people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when it is after ſuch grieuous vexation as was in the Demoniakes in the Goſpell, when it is with the health of the parties, and preſent freedome from all former vexations dy Satan, wee need not doubt of it in any ſort. For the viſible departure of Satan, I anſwered you euen very now.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:9803:19"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 87. 88<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 43</note> Beſides, I alleage for Diſpoſſeſsion, <hi>Satans deſire of repoſſeſsion, which is neuer but after he is throwne out.</hi> You returne a double an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, firſt, <hi>that theſe wordes, I will returne to the houſe from whence I came, &amp;c. be metaphoricall.</hi> Wee remember indeede your monſtrous abſurditie in making <hi>all things whatſouer, spoken of Angels, and diuels in the ſcripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be Meaphoricall.</hi> But as I haue ſhewed you, manie are not Metaphoricall, ſo neither is this repecting the ſentence of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 45</note>it. The words be part of a ſimilitude, as is plaine by the reddition, <hi>So ſhall it be to this wicked generation.</hi> The whole ſtandeth thus. As when an vncleane ſpirit goeth forth of a man, paſſeth through drie places ſeeking reſt, and findeth none: then faith, I will returne to my houſe, &amp;c. entring againe in, the laſt eſtate of that man is worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo ſhal it be to this wicked generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now to find what paſt of this ſentence is Metaphoricall, we are to know that a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is twofold. One which is contracted &amp; ſhut vp in one word, properly called a Metaphor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the other diſplaid &amp; ſpread open, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſting of all the parts at large, and is tearmed by the name of the generall, a Similitude. For the figuratiue part in either, the reaſon is one in both. Therfore as in a contracted ſimilitude, the Metaphor lyeth in the word that is borrowed, and not in that from<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whence it is borrowed, ſo in the larger ſimilitude, the metaphoricall part of it reſteth in the Reddition, not in the Propoſition. For example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour nouriſheth Artes: the word Nouriſheth being borrowed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meats nouriſhing the bodie, is a Metaphor as it is applyed to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Artes, but attributed to his proper termes, it is no Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, as to ſay thus, Meat nouriſheth the body. In like manner (to make a full Similitude of it, in this ſort) As meat nouriſheth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo Honour nouriſheth Artes, the Metaphoricall part of the whole, lyeth in the latter member, not in the firſt. So likewiſe when our Sauiour ſaith, As a man deliuered from the poſſeſsion of Satan, and receiuing him in againe, is in worſe caſe after, then before: So the nation of the Iewes, once deliuered from the kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, ſo long as the church of God was amongſt them, and comming into his ſubiection againe by refuſing Chriſt, ſhould bee in more miſerable condition then in any former time: the Metaphoricall ſentence of this Similitude, is in the laſt branch of it, not in the firſt. Not becauſe there be no Metaphoricall words in the firſt, as Drie places, houſe emptie, ſwept, garniſhed. &amp;c. but for that wee now ſpeake of Metaphoricall ſentences, not of words. I frame my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Propoſition of the Similitude, the ſentence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9803:19"/>
is literall and hiſtoricall, not from the Reddition, whoſe ſenſe is allegoricall. Now then i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a man ſhould reaſon thus: The Reddition of the Similitude is Metaphoricall, therefore the whole is metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, it is all one as if one ſhould ſay, The blacke Moore bath white teeth, therefore he is all white. Which kinde of argument euerie chimney-ſweeper would deride: and yet thus you reaſon from this place, and make it one of your chiefeſt props to vpholde your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd concluſions with. But vnto this place I added another, where our Sauiour ſaith to the vncleane ſpirit, <hi>Come out of him, and enter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 25.</note>
               <hi>no more into him.</hi> Was our Sauiours prohibition here in vaine? was this caution altogether needleſſe and ſuperſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uo us? How chaunce you paſſ ouer this place, withoutanſweri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g one word vnto it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was too plaine: and you two could not agree where the Metaphor ſhould lie, &amp; therefore thought better to ſlip it ouer, then by hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, and bewraying your owne abſurdities to marre all. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entrie therfore of Satan is plaine by the Scriptures: ſo that we need not the teſtimonie of any experience: yet I haue adioyned in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> the report of the children diſpoſſeſſed, and the euidence of many godly then preſent, which perceiued by their agonie, and the words of their reſiſtance, what Satan attempted. You trifle ouer this with greater childiſhneſſe then appeared in the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though but nine or tenne yeares old, and therefore I diſdaine to anſwere it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Againe for proofe of diſpoſſeſsion, I alleage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>continuance of the parties health ſince:</hi> you anſwere: <hi>Their former fittes were but counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 90.</note>
               <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelues haue confeſſed.</hi> A ſtale proofe of their counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and anſwered before. The ſeuen in Lancaſhire neuer confeſſed any counterfeiting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 91. 92. 93.</note> Thus hauing confirmed Diſpoſſeſsion, I remoue that vſuall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, ſhewing it is now no miracle, for that it is not done by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power of Chriſt in bodily preſence, as he ſometimes did it when he was here conuerſant on earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor by any committed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary power to men but by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſting an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er as the means<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you anſwere firſt: <hi>as if I affirmed Chriſts abſolute power to be ceaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d:</hi> which I affirme not, but account ſuch affirmation blaſphemie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He is not now preſent in bodie on earth, but worketh by his abſolute authoritie ſtill. Secondly, <hi>If Chriſts abſolute author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then the worke is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miraculous, as euer.</hi> Which is a flat vntruth, as I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e proued at large in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our tenth Dialogue. For works done by men as inſtruments are diſtinguiſhed by the maner of working, and not by the principall cauſe. you ſay <hi>my Similitude from the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9803:20"/>
Queene, and Lord Chauncelour is too abſurd: for firſt, it is a caſe which neuer ſhall be, and ſo cannot illuſtrate.</hi> I had thought that <hi>fictaſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo</hi> might haue had ſome force. But ſurely as you are full of newe Diuinitie, ſo I thinke you haue ſwallowed <hi>Margaritam Philoſophiae,</hi> you breake out on euerie occaſion with ſuch wonderfull new axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes of Logicke. I intended that Similitude to the manner onely of Chriſts working, and you would extend it to the <hi>like glory of his works now,</hi> cleane beyond my purpoſe, and any good probabilitie. For are not Chriſts workes more glorious, when together with him ſelfe his ſeruants worke extraordinarily, as they did in the time of miracles, then now, when his ſeruants working is only ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But you will make the ſame ſimilitude ouerthrow all miracles now, which I will yeeld for any, but for your ſelues: for you haue a priuiledge to do miracles, as is apparant in your tenth Dialogue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 94.</note> Hitherto for <hi>Dispoſſeſsion,</hi> now for the <hi>meanes:</hi> which I affirme with many godly and learned of auncient and our owne times, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 17. 21</note>to be <hi>faſting and prayer,</hi> out of the words of our Sauiour, <hi>This kinde go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th not out but by faſting and prayer.</hi> Where I calling it a <hi>Secret ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> oppoſe it to more euident places: you catch at the word, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29, 29</note>come vpon me with <hi>Secret things belong onely to God.</hi> He that ſhould deale with you had neede, as the Lawyers in writing their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, rather haue twentie words to ſpare, then to want one. You would proue, <hi>theſe words did onely belong to the Diſciples, becauſe the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 95. 96.</note>
               <hi>queſtion was made by them, and the anſwere to them.</hi> The Iayler in the 16. of the <hi>Acts</hi> ſayd to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, What muſt I do to be ſaued?</hi> They anſwere him: <hi>Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt and thou ſhalt be ſaued,</hi> &amp;c. Doth this Scripture now only belong to the Iaylor, becauſe this queſtion was made by him, &amp; the anſwer vnto him? Of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 17. 21</note>this kind be infinite other places. For interpretation of theſe words of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> I haue ſhewed you how I conceiue of them in your ninth Dialogue. Which expoſition varieth ſomwhat from my former, not becauſe I cannot maintaine it againſt any thing you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, but becauſe I ſeeke after truth, and not after vaine iangling. If you can ſhew me any better, I will be readie alſo to change this. In meane ſeaſon vnderſtand how I reaſon from hence for the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al meanes of Faſting and prayer, which are mentioned by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in this place, either as helpes to the extraordinarie and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous faith of the Apoſtles, or elſe of the ordinarie. But they are not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 17.</note>mentioned as helpes to the extraordinarie: for miraculous faith in the leaſt quantity, though no more then a graine of muſtard ſeede
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9803:20"/>
was able without theſe helpes to expell any diuell. Beſides they could not be helpes to that, which in it ſelfe had no being. For the Diſciples had vtterly loſt their miraculous faith, elſe they had ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſpirit. This alſo the word <hi>Apiſtia, incrdulity</hi> doth note vn to vs. And an helpe is a conioyned force, which coniunction cannot be, where there is nothing to ioyne withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore they bee propo unded in this place as helpes to the ordinary faith, and ſo to haue a perpetuall ordinarie vſe, when like occaſion is miniſtred to vs. Againe, euery Exception is a compendious ſpeech, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding in it two propoſitions, as, <hi>Except a man be borne againe, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 33. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 44. <hi>Act.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. 31</note>
               <hi>ſee the kingdome of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> wherein is concluded alſo this, If f a man be borne againe he can ſe the kingdome of God. So, <hi>None can come vnto me except the Father draw him.</hi> Euery one can come vnto mee, whom my Father draweth. Againe, <hi>Except theſe abide in the ſhip, you cannot be ſaued.</hi> If theſe abide in the ſhip, you can be ſaued. And ſo in all other. In like manner, <hi>This kind doth not go forth, but by prayer and faſting.</hi> This kind doth go forth by prayer and faſting. Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let men o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> iudgement determine whether here be not an euident confirmation of the ordinarie courſe of the Church in dealing after this maner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whether it be not exceeding boldneſſe, our Sauiour affirming in ſuch ſort as is declared<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That this kind doth goe forth by prayer and faſting, for any to open his mouth licenciouſly agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt it, and to diſgrace it by al opprobrious tearmes he can. From hence too you may ſee, the ſimilitude drawne from the Phyſition ſaying to his patient, daungerouſly ſicke of the Pleuriſy, <hi>You cannot liue, except you bleed,</hi> was to good purpoſe, if you could iudge what is to purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It is too tedious to repeat all your vntruthes, your abſurd <hi>Non ſequiturs,</hi> and idle profes. As if <hi>I thought it vnreaſonable for Christ to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 99</note>
               <hi>reproue his Diſciples negligence: if Chriſts anſwere were not proper to the Diſciples, it was no anſwere: if he directed not his ſpeech to the Diſciples onely, he ſpake to no body preſent.</hi> This mettal craues no touchſtonne, it ſhewes it ſelfe by the eye what it is: therefore a knocke with an hammer is ſufficient So, <hi>If this anſwere of Chriſt propounded an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for al ages to come, there is an ordinance without an appointed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go the ſame.</hi> Indeed this would be ſtraunge for Accidents to walke alone without ſubiects. It is a difficult matter to finde who ſhould be the ſubiect of faſting and praver: ſo likewiſe too of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.</note>kingdom of God, which our Sauiour ordaineth to be ſought in the firſt place, and food and rayment in the ſecond, if we could tell who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9803:21"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>g.</hi> 100.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſides <hi>ſucceeding ages that could expell this cumberſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld haue more power the eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtles bad,</hi> which is falſe: for the Apoſtles, their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſaith not fayling, could expell any diuell. Fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, <hi>The Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>les ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aile in not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing this ordinance vnto vs:</hi> concerning which ynough hath beene ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in the ninth Dialogue. I aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, <hi>it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance in this place, becauſe M Darr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>th it hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ene a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ordinance fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the beginning.</hi> I anſwere, I doe not refe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the originall to this place, but onely the Confirmation, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iath.</hi> 19 99 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12. 27 <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 13.</note>no otherwiſe then I make Matrimony an eſtabliſhed ordinance by our Sauiour Chriſt, he rene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the inſtitution of it.</p>
            <p>Againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I argue the meanes of faſting and prayer from the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample of the Iewes Church in our Sauiours time: wherin ſome did caſt forth diuels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet were not in the number of our Sauiours Diſciples, neither did it in his name. You anſwere, I <hi>contrarie my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, affirming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e where, they did it by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inger of God:</hi> I reply, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>do not contrary your ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but are euer li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e your ſelues, moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly concluding the ſelfe ſame working of the inſtrument, from the ſame maner of the principall agent: whereas the chiefe doer being the ſame, may and doth worke by the inſtrument diuerſly. <hi>Againe,</hi> ſay you <hi>by mine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wne conſeſsion, this ordinance as then was not eſtabliſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I anſwere, is was not ſo plainely, as when our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auiour con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmed it by theſe words, yet in generall it was, and practiſed in the Church before. Moreouer, ſay you, <hi>Thoſe in our Sauiours time beſides</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22</note>
               <hi>his Diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> caſt out diuels by miraculous faith only,</hi> for which you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage the ſeuenth of <hi>Matth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w</hi> I reply, this ſcripture ſpeaketh onely of the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection of Satan but ſheweth not in what manner the ſame was performed, nor when<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We do not leane vpon any <hi>doubtfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties,</hi> as you would Rhetorically declare, if ye knew how<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we <hi>take the Lords holy name in vain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> nor <hi>pray with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as you prate both without wit and conſcience. I paſſe ouer your foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries concerning K. <hi>Wright,</hi> &amp; your ſixe lies at one clap<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contained <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 103. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 104.</note>in ſeuen lines, as I can proue to your ſhame. But what ſpeake I of ſixe, when I dare ſay there be ſixe hundred leaſings in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our two vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lumes? VVe neede not take things of whole ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men by retale: it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y matter to know b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing whoſe children ve are</p>
            <p>That <hi>Chriſts speech ought not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>propriated to the Diſciples,</hi> hath bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e declared. Neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o I <hi>ſay and unſay</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou falſly charge me. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 105. 106.</note>The communication was betweene our Sauiour and his Diſciples, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the ordinance there mentioned is common to all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et <hi>Phyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> ſit theſe <hi>variable anſwers,</hi> as hee miſcals them, doth tell vs <hi>a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9803:21"/>
tale of an H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which comming to a Farmers houſe, and blowing his fingers to warme them, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ottage to coole them, was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt packing by the Farmer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as a diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbling c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpanion.</hi> But, to requite you tale, what if the like Hermit had come to ſome good mans houſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on his face a faire ſhining viſarce with <hi>A. W.</hi> written vpon it, ſhould vpon occaſion haue his viſard ſhaken off, and vnder it ſhewe another face, ſigned with <hi>I. De.</hi> Might not the good man iuſtly abhorre this double fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed gueſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>moniſh all honeſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panie to beware of him? I will pard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n you your ſport at <hi>faſt and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 107.</note>
               <hi>looſe for a ſhilling,</hi> though I might iuſtly make it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſter vnto you, then you would vnlooſe againe in haſte. Put where is the <hi>contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> I pray you, <hi>in making th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe words to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee spoken to the Diſciples, and yet not onely to be vnderſtood of them?</hi> You would collect it after this manner, <hi>Becauſe that weakneſſe of faith, and the kind of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re the two in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wherefore the child was not deliuered.</hi> And that which is an impediment to anie, is alſo proper to the ſame partie, if we will beleeue your Metaphyſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes. For you muſt needs deriue your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption <note place="margin">
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 4. 1. 2.</note>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m hence. As if the Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aelites being ſhut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of the land of promiſe for their v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>beleefe, this impediment ſhould bee ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to them, that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re but themſelues ſhould be excluded for the ſame: which abſurditie is of that nature, that if your ſticke of faſt and looſe were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good ſound cudgell, you deſerue to be well labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red about the ſhoulders with it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut what ſhould I purſue your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall abſurdities? To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake after ſuch ſcatterers were to fill a cart, rather then ones lap. In briefe for your whole diſpute, to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue <hi>theſe words only to belong to the Diſciples:</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> incredulitie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſsion of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.</note>prayer and faſting were impediments onely to the nine Diſciples, (for <hi>Peter, Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were not of this number) then they can be impediments to no body elſe. And ſo <hi>Peter, Iames &amp; Iohn</hi> ſhould caſt out any kind of ſpirit notwithſtanding the like incredulity, and omiſsion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſting and prayer. Yea all other Chriſtians whatſoeuer ſhould alſo in like manner. For what ſhould hinder them, if they haue no impediment? And what impediment can they haue, theſe two being onely proper to the nine Diſciples? See now how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently you tie <hi>theſe words to the Diſciples onely,</hi> permitting larger power to all other Chriſtians then to them. The contradiction you here charge me with is lame. It is palpably falſe, that 1 <hi>pag.</hi> 49. <hi>of the Doctrine au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, there are ſome kind of spirits, which the Apoſtles (with all their power) could not poſsibly expell, but by prayer and fasting.</hi> Of this very errour I do by ſundrie reaſons from pag. 44. of the <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9803:22"/>
vnto page 48. confute <hi>Stapleton</hi> and <hi>Thyrcus,</hi> which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you charge vpon me, &amp; againe ſticke not to ſay, that <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton, Thyrcus, and my ſelfe agree herein,</hi> ſo ſhameleſſe are you. But ſpecially you make your ſelues merie with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction, pag. 111. 112. I anſwere, The Diſciples their not expelling the diuell out of the <hi>Lunatike,</hi> when they were deſtitute of miraculous faith, letteth not but that by miraculous faith they could expell any diuel. Theſe I truſt may agree together, without cutting the throat one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>That which you talke of <hi>helping their weake miraculous faith by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pa.</hi> 113, &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>faſting and prayer,</hi> is already anſwered. Further, I ſhewing that <hi>faſting and prayer were not required as helpes in this place to miraculous fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> ſay, that <hi>Miraculous faith is of that kind, which is giuen without means to certaine men:</hi> whereupon it muſt needs follow, that there being an <hi>Apiſtia,</hi> an vtter defect of miraculous faith in theſe Diſciples, it was not to be recouered by faſting and prayer. You anſwere, <hi>It was not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 9.</note>
               <hi>begotton without meanes, becauſe it was giuen by inspiration of God.</hi> By which you make the holy Spirit to bee a meanes: whereas a meanes is but an inſtrument: And the holye Ghoſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the other two perſons of holie Trinity is alwayes a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall efficient. Thus you confound heauen and earth together, &amp; make nothing in the world to be done without means: neither any thing in the world to bee more then ordinary: for whatſoeuer is done by the ſame vſuall and neuer ceaſing meanes, muſt needs bee reputed ordinarie. There be few places in the fielde more repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſpring with ſtincking nettles and weedes, then your whole booke with ſuch poyſon full Hemlockes as theſe. But with all we haue a Diſcourſe of an <hi>Habituall &amp; Actuall miraculous faith:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 114.</note>whereof the <hi>habitual is begotten by the Spirit and the word.</hi> Seeing therefore theſe cauſes cannot alwayes be effectleſſe, and that they be euer working in the Church till the end of the world, it cannot be auoided but that Miraculous faith ſhould be in the Church for euer: And the rather if we conſider, what by your ſaying <hi>miraculous faith is:</hi> which you define to be nothing els, but <hi>an vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uted perſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, by which we firmly beleeue, that there is nothing impoſsible to God:</hi> But all the faithfull do vndoubtly beleeue this, and therefore we haue ſtill <hi>Miraculous faith</hi> remaining amongſt vs, and ſhal haue ſo long as the Church ſoiornes on earth: yea the very diuels beleeue this and ſo hauing miraculous faith, by your leaden rule ſhall bee workers of true miracles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I adde, they which were endued with the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9803:22"/>
miraculous faith, had beſides the perſwaſion of <hi>Gods omnipotencie,</hi> an vndoubted perſwaſion of the will of God, for the effecting of the wonderful matters, which beſides or contrarie to nature they atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the good of the Church. Now for as much as the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and aſſurance of the ſaid will of God</hi> is not to bee had from the <hi>word,</hi> therefore the written word is not the onely ground<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>worke of miraculous faith, neither doth it come <hi>by the hearing thereof,</hi> as you affirme. For <hi>Actuall faith,</hi> you will haue it <hi>a ſpeciall motion from the ſpirit of God, raiſed vp extraordinarily,</hi> whereby <hi>the action of faith</hi> ſhall not proceed from the <hi>Habit</hi> as from the next cauſe, as the action of iuſtice cometh from the habit of iuſtice, and ſo in all other qualities of that kind, but there ſhall be ſomething in Actuall faith extraordinarily more then was in the Habituall. If a man had your ſharpnes he might quickly go beyond <hi>Actius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nauius,</hi> that cut the whetſtone in peeces with his raſor. For <hi>the increaſe of miraculous faith by means,</hi> it is but needles to ſtand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering we affirm an vtter defect therof at this time in the diſciples, not ſome coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſparkes remaining in them, to be raiſed into flames by faſting and praier. For true miraculous faith how litle ſoeuer, is able with out theſe helps, to atchiue her deſined worke. But then you will ſay, yea in effect do ſay, that <hi>the Apoſtles did ſuperfluouſly ioine praier</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 116.</note>
               <hi>with it.</hi> I anſwer, no more ſuperfluouſly, then the Church doth ioyne Sacraments with the word. Faith of it ſelf is ſufficient, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Chriſt vnto ſaluation, and this faith is begotten by the word: Yet Sacraments haue their neceſſary vſe, not to inable faith to that, which it could not with out them, but to confirme and ſtrengthen it to doe her worke more cherfully, and with fuller aſſurance. Praier is the general inſtrument to be vſed in all holy workes what ſoeuer: and therfore the Apoſtles had warrant for their praier, &amp; were free from all will-worſhip therin. I omit here <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 117. 118</note>for breuitie fiue of your ſlanders, and two contradictions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you charge me, my ſelfe being not author of any one of the contradictory propoſions.</p>
            <p>I prouing that theſe wordes in S. <hi>Mathewe (this kind goeth not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 17. 21</note>
               <hi>out,</hi> &amp;c. belong not peculiarly to the Diſciples, ſay, that <hi>if our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had rebuked them for not faſting &amp; praying, they might haue excuſed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 119 120. 121.</note>
               <hi>their want of time,</hi> you trifle exceedinglye about this: at laſt you affoord vs this worthy anſwere, that <hi>conſidering our Sauiours ſtaying in the mount</hi> (which for all the circumſtances you can alleadge can not be long) <hi>they had time ynough to pray. Antiquum obtinct Crito,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9803:23"/>
you muſt run your old byas, &amp; impudently flap vs in the mouth with <hi>time for prayer,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the queſtion is of <hi>time for faſting and prayer.</hi> Againe, you wil haue theſe words, <hi>This kind goeth not forth but by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and prayer, to be no ſever all reaſon rendred by our Sauiour, why his Diſciples failed in their purpoſe:</hi> whereas we haue ſhewed, it is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct thing from Miraculous faith, and not neceſſarily ioyned with it: and therefore not to concurre in making one reaſon with the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 122. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi> 123. 124</note>ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Moreouer ſay I, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Apoſtles in each weaknes of this faith, muſt of neceſsity haue betaken themſelues to faſting and prayer, they ſhould haue bene a whole day about a miracles the exerciſe of faſting requiring this ſpace, which would haue bene great hinderance to their speedy tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell ouer the whole earth.</hi> You anſwere, <hi>This is Iudaiſme.</hi> Belike alſo it is Iudaiſme for Chriſtians to pray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe the Iewes did ſo. But vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand, good Reader, that the practiſe only of ſuch cereremonies as the Lord appointed to be a difference betweene the Iewes, and other people, is Iudaiſme, not the exerciſe of ſuch duties, as be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both. That which you doubt <hi>what ſhould become of the other part of the day, if the diuell ſhould be caſt forth before noone,</hi> beſeemeth men which acknowledge no other ſeruice of God, but for their owne turnes. Is there no duty of thankſgiuing? no requeſt for ſtrength to the party diſpoſſeſſed? no deſire that the eye-witneſſes might profit by it? you would haue Chriſtians ſerue God, as the dog his maiſter for a bone. The reſt is vnworthy to be repeated, &amp; ſo was this, but that I would giue the Reader a taſte. But what ſay you, that wil not haue a faſt to continue <hi>for a day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to A Walker, alias</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi> 5.</note>
               <hi>Io. Deacon?</hi> who in a booke of his called <hi>the Footpath to faſting,</hi> ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that <hi>in the day of our faſt, we muſt be exerciſed in hearing, applying, and praying for the rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uing of God his iudgements, euen from morning to night?</hi> Do I (you falſe tongues) in <hi>pag.</hi> 48. and 49. of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 125.</note>ſay, that <hi>the Apoſtles ſhould haue ſtirred vp their weake faith by faſting and prayer,</hi> when I ſpend thoſe whole pages to proue the contrary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O palpable ſlaunder, and extreame impudencie! Likewiſe you ſay, I affirme elſe where, <hi>The Apoſtles faith was ſo ſtrong as it needed no meanes to ſtirre vp the ſame.</hi> And I would tell you, you ſay vntruly, but that your skore is ſo full that now you be deſperate. Of theſe two baſtardly propoſitions, conceiued and brought forth by your ſelues, and not by me, you frame a <hi>Contradiction:</hi> ſaying therupon, that <hi>I will turne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re I burne, yea with the turning of an hand, turne the cat in the pan:</hi> and then you tell my <hi>pupils,</hi> they <hi>may be peſtilent proud
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9803:23"/>
of ſuch a turne-about tutor.</hi> Here wee may beholde, as your honeſt dealing with me, ſo your eloquence and modeſtie.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I auouching <hi>the Apoſtles ſtrong faith after Pentecoſt, able for miracles whatſoeuer, and therefore vnlikely the Lord ſhould appoint a peculiar courſe for them, for ſo ſhort a time as from his transfiguration till then:</hi> you collect from hence <hi>the weaknes of their faith till Penticoſt:</hi> which I graunt you, and more then that, namely, that their miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous faith was vtterly extinct at this time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therfore no vſe of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and prayer for the extraordinarie work, but onely as it ſerued to the vſual maner of the Church in this caſe. But you wil proue <hi>the apoſtles miraculous faith might faile a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter Pentecoſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>their faith failed ſometimes in doctrine and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> That we may vnderſtand your meaning, what do y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by Doctrine? what by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Doctrine vſuall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is publike teaching and inſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment priuate thinking and opinion. Did the Apoſtles erre in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like teaching? You ſaye, <hi>The Apoſtles and bretheren which were in Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, thought the word of God was not to be preached to the Gentils.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 11. 2.</note>You ground this ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe wordes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>And when Peter was aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruſalem, they of the circumciſion contended againſt him.</hi> VVho contended with him? The Apoſtles, ſay you, but without any warrant from the text. It ſeemeth <hi>S. Luke</hi> hauing mentioned the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the firſt verſe, doth of purpoſe in the ſecond vſe theſe generall termes, <hi>They of the circumciſion,</hi> to diſtinguiſh theſe contenders with <hi>Peter,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles. It may be the Apoſtles did not yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o clearly vnderſtand this miſtery, yet it is not likelie they were in this ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no more but equall to the weake brethren, whereby the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould ioyne in contention with them. Grant we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an errour here, it was only in <hi>iudgement,</hi> not in doctrine. And as for <hi>Peters not going rightly to the truth of the Gospell,</hi> it was not error <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gat.</hi> 2. 13. 14</note>either in doctrine or iudgement, but a timorous diſsimulation for the time. <hi>Iohn his falling downe before an Angell,</hi> was errour through <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue.</hi> 19. 10</note>ſodaine paſsion, not proceeding from ſetled iudgement, much leſſe auouched in publike teaching. Conſidering therefore theſe places proue not that <hi>the Apoſtles erred in doctrine and iudgement,</hi> and that the <hi>Lord</hi> doth principall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> promiſe that <hi>the Spirit of truth ſhould l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 13 &amp; 14. 26. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note>
               <hi>them into all truth: and bring all things to their remembrance which Chriſt had told them,</hi> whereupon they be called <hi>Skilfull Maiſter-buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and the Church is ſaid to be <hi>built vpon the foundation of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and apoſtles.</hi> It is admirable you dare ſo conſidently auouch ſuch an aſſertion, vpon ſo little or rather no warrant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9803:24"/>
conſequence. You childiſhly cauill at my ſpeech, where I ſay, <hi>Their faith did not faile them, after they receiued the holy Ghoſt in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 127. &amp;c</note>
               <hi>That f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe:</hi> as if I had attributed ſuch a fulneſſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as is not inci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent to a creature: and yet I expreſly diſtinguiſh it by note of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 55. &amp; 13. 9. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 41. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 2. 4</note>
               <hi>That fulneſſe,</hi> that is, ſuch a plentifull meaſure as I had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of before. Such an one, as was ſaid of <hi>Stephen,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat <hi>hee was ful of the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and of <hi>Paul:</hi> and of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when ſhee brake forth into that heauenly ſalutation of the bleſſed virgin, <hi>that ſhe was filled with the holy ghoſt.</hi> The ſame is ſaid of <hi>Zacha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> when he prophecied, and of the Apoſtles, <hi>that they were filled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the holy ghoſt.</hi> And all theſe in the Concret<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in the Abſtract without all limitation to haue the fulneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Spirit, belongeth onely to a diuine perſon, the Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that whatſoeuer perſon hath the ſimple fulneſſe of the Spirit, the ſame is God, as well as hee who hath the fulneſſe of the Godhead. Of Chriſt his fulneſſe (to whom the Father hath not giuen his Spirit by meaſure) do all the elect receiue, not the fulnes it ſelfe, but grace for grace, that is, graces or gifts of the Spirit heaped vpon graces: euery one according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, ſome eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntil their cup runne ouer. All which diſcourſe when at laſt you <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 133.</note>conclude, that <hi>howſoeuer the Apoſtles were ſubiect to errour, yet they could not poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iblie erre ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long as they heard the voice of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and but followed the onely directions of the ſpirit of truth: And that they did neuer vniuerſally erre: Moreouer, that they did neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cline from the foundation it ſelfe:</hi> &amp; laſtly, that <hi>they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re recalled from their e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> what ſingular thing do you aſcribe to the Apoſtles, that is not com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon to all beleeuers? Are not the Apoſtles to be preferred aboue all other Miniſters of the Goſpell, and beleeuers ſince theire dayes? Yet you ſeeme to put them in the very ſame ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nay, you ſay in the top of the ſame page, that <hi>there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſome F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the Apoſtles, which onely but ſlipped from humane infirmities, and that theſe (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow glorious ſoeuer in ſhew) are not the teſtimony of Ieſus, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the ſpirit of proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cie.</hi> you speake here very daungerouſly, that I ſay no worſe.</p>
            <p>You argue <hi>the defect of the Apoſtles miraculous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith,</hi> from their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 135. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 29 30. &amp; 9. 40 &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 8. 8</note>
               <hi>praying in working miracles,</hi> which rather is an argument for the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuance of it. For if it had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in vtterly extin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it had not bene to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e obtained by prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if you ſay Prayer declareth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaknes of it, and that you meane ſuch weakneſſe, as without prayer ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not beene able to effect the worke, it is falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath beene oft <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9803:24"/>
vnto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if you take weakneſſe for ſome leſſe meaſure of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 17.</note>cheerefulneſſe, which had neede be ſtirred by inuocation of Gods holy name, I graunt you ſuch a weakneſſe, but this is too weake to ſtrengthen any whit your cauſe. you charge mee falſly in ſaying, I <hi>denie that the apoſtles faith might &amp; did faile before they were filled with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct. pag.</hi> 46, 48 <hi>Doct.</hi> 49 <hi>pag.</hi> 136</note>
               <hi>the holy Spirit.</hi> I know not how oft I affirme this, which you ſay <hi>is the very point</hi> I <hi>denie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Neither do I ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>it was but fortie dayes betweene Chriſt his transfigi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation, and Pentecoſt.</hi> I do writtingly let paſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of your lies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is a trouble to repeate them. you ſee <hi>no inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience to approper theſe words, This kind goeth not forth but by faſting &amp; prayer, to the Diſciples themſelues:</hi> whereas if faſting and prayer had beene neceſſarie as helpes to their weake faith, that could not ſtand which our Sauiour hath immediately before affirmed, that ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith as a graine of Muſtard ſeede ſhould be able to do the greateſt miracles. Howe this diſtinction of diuels is to be vnderſtoode, wee haue ſufficiently declared in the <hi>Doctrine.</hi> you make a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <note place="margin">Doct. p. <hi>51<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note>partition, when you interpret <hi>This kind,</hi> only to diſtinguiſh <hi>diuets from other creatures.</hi> The nature of a partition is, that the thing which is parted ſhould be common to all the members. as in this place, <hi>creatures going out</hi> is the Generall agreeing to both the Specials, in this ſort. Of creatures that go out of man ſome are diuels, and they go not out but by faſting and prayer: ſome are of other kinde, and theſe of what nature ſoeuer goe out of a man without faſting and prayer Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is man now become a cage for all creatures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Indeed the old Philoſophers had woont to ſay, that Man is a little world: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou will giue vs a ſenſible vnderſtanding o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, if horſes, be ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and lyons, fowles, and creeping things of all kind, may haue an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in him. You haue beene ſo carefull all this while to free man from poſſeſsion of diuels, that in the meane ſeaſon you haue made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im a fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſt to containe all ſauage beaſts in. I pray you what kind of creature doth lodge in your owne breaſtes? But you ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 137.</note>
               <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kind cannot be referred to the diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls amongst themſelues, becauſe they be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all of one kind as angels be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo men.</hi> Profoundly ſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as if <hi>kind</hi> did onely note eſſence, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſometimes quality and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you brought vs euen now an example of <hi>threwes, The beſt of this kind is ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>miſh ynough wherby</hi> you ſaid, <hi>wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n were ſeuered from men by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fore or kind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Is difference of ſexe difference of Eſſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeake of doceitfull men, This kind of men is not to bee tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tterers and ambitious perſons This kind of men ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all to pleaſe thoſe in authority<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of ſuch as haue made ſhip wracke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:9803:25"/>
a good conſcience, This kind of men groweth worſe &amp; worſe. Now tell me, you <hi>Anſwerers,</hi> whether <hi>Kind</hi> will carie no other ſenſe but that, wherewith you cauill as beſeemeth freſh Sophiſters. Againe, it is admirable, you could find no other ſimilitude to declare the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 138.</note>of diuels by, but onely the <hi>whole ſtate of this kingdom of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> comparing our moſt gracious <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> Gods Lieutenant amongſt vs (I tremble to ſpeake it) to the Prince of darkneſſe, and all the inferiour honourable orders of <hi>Dukes, Earles, Lords, Iudges, Iuſtices, Knights, Gentlemen, yomen,</hi> &amp;c. to the lower ſort of diuels. Could any men forget themſelues ſo much, as that againſt all good maners, againſt honeſty, againſt Chriſtianitie, yea, againſt nature it ſelfe, which hath printed in the minds of ſubiects all loyall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent reſpect towards their moſt worthy Soueraigne, and in the hearts of inferiours all dutifull regard of their honourable Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, that you ſhoulde vtter ſuch blaſphemie againſt Gods ſacred Miniſters, and ſo noble and ſo flouriſhing eſtate as this is? He that priuiledged this, deſerues hee ſhould priuiledge no more. You thought to lade your <hi>Exorciſt</hi> with the enuy of ſo odious a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon: but all wiſe men will ſee, your ſelues are the <hi>Exorciſt,</hi> and all the reſt of the perſons in your books, whom ye make to ſpeak what and how ye pleaſe: and therefore whatſoeuer they offende, they ought to be whipped on your backs. I take not vpon me to define of the <hi>ſeuerall orders of diuels</hi> farther then the ſacred word of truth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 140. &amp;c</note>is my guide. You contrariwiſe, that you might oppoſe your ſelues againſt me, ſticke not to bend your forces againſt the verie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For you will haue nothing now amongſt them, but a <hi>meere confuſion, and a ſtate without all order:</hi> notwithſtanding our Sauiour <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. 25 &amp;c. &amp; 25 41.</note>teacheth, that the power of darkneſſe is a kingdome: that there is a Prince of this kingdom called <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> and inferiour degrees cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his <hi>angels</hi> (which whether they be all of them equall, or no with out diſtinction or difference in any reſpect whatſoeuer, you ſhould haue conſidered from theſe words, <hi>He taketh vnto him ſeuen other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits worſe then himſelfe,</hi> &amp; not vainly to haue trifled about the word <hi>Exuſia)</hi> that there is a kind of policie of concord maintained amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, whereby this kingdom is vpholden. Theſe things are plainly taught, and are ſuch as no Chriſtian may gainſay, yet you would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow all this, ſtriuing for ſuch a blended mingle amongſt them, as is vtterly void of any the leaſt diſtinction. But it is a true ſaying, Fooles whileſt they labour one euill to ſhun, into the contrarie preſently runne. VVhereas in theſe words, <hi>This kind goeth, not forth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9803:25"/>
but by prayer &amp; fasting,</hi> I haue obſerued foure thinges: <hi>That there are two kinds of diuels: That one is more difficultly expelled then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: that the child was poſſeſſed with one of the worſer kind: that thence partly it was wherefore the Diſciples caſt him not forth:</hi> you returne, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 154.</note>
               <hi>They which want arte to analyze the Scriptures, may here learne to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butcher a text,</hi> with Rhetorike ill beſeeming vnmannerly clownes. But tell me, is there no difference between <hi>Analyzing,</hi> and making <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 155</note>collections from a text? Prate no more of the <hi>extraordinarie faith of the Diſciples,</hi> except you can make it good by ſound reaſon they were indued with ſuch kind of faith at that time. Our Sauiour faith there was an <hi>Apiſtia</hi> in them, a thorough defect, wherby only they failed in that extraordinarie courſe they attempted. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 157. 158.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But now you wil ſhew <hi>the impieties, abſurdities and dangers which follow of this doctrine.</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt, <hi>it is impietie to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouch any thing for truth that is not.</hi> I acknowledge it is a greate impiety: but this doctrine doth not ſo. Secondly, <hi>Lying wonders are the marks of Antichriſt.</hi> I anſwere, you ly falſly, when you make the caſting forth of Satan by payer and faſting to be a l ying wonder. Thirdly, <hi>it is impiety to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme fasting and prayer (ex operato) may effect ſuch a worke.</hi> It is impietie indeed, but you may as truly charge me with this affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as you might charge any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſound hearted Chriſtian that knowes <hi>M<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deacon,</hi> with affirming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he is an honeſt man. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, <hi>it is impiety to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phane prayer and faſting without warrant from the word.</hi> We graunt alſo this, but withall ioyne vnto it, That it is no leſſe impietie to call that prophaning of prayer and faſting, which is warranted by the word, as in this caſe it is. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtly, <hi>it is impiety</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to make prayer and faſting which of God are apprinted to bee helpes vnto ſaith, a ſole meanes without faith for expelling of diuels.</hi> I ſubſcribe vnto it and wiſh with all my heart, that he which ſaith ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may receiue the reward of a deceiuer: but if ſuch cogitation was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer farre from my breaſt, that ſuch impudent ſlaunderers might be branded in their forehads with this marke: <hi>Falſe accuſers of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> I doubt not but you haue read theſe words of the <hi>Diſcouerer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> (who neuer ſpeaketh vntruly for mee, whatſouer hee doth againſt <note place="margin">Diſeo. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note>me) <hi>M. Darrell confeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the neceſsitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f faith in the ordinarie means.</hi> Your <hi>abſurdities</hi> (for ſo they are indeed) with the <hi>daungers</hi> partly fooliſhly, &amp; partly falſly imagined, what ſhould I vouchſafe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate them? I will leaue theſe and ſuch like to the Reader, able now by that which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beene ſaide, for all your maske to diſcerne you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:9803:26"/>
               <note place="margin">159,</note> You vpbraide me <hi>with hiding my ſelfe for feare of perill.</hi> I haue learned by the commandement and example of Chriſt Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his Apoſtles, and of the Martyrs in all ages, that I may, nay, ought to giue place to the rage of man, eſpecially not forſaking in the meane ſeaſon any duty that concernes me. Yet that you may know I am not cleane runne away, by that time you haue read my <hi>Suruey</hi> and this <hi>Reply,</hi> tell me whether you haue not met with ſome bodie to cope with in the field. You will not allow Chriſtians, <hi>if they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 160</note>
               <hi>perceiue not their firſt endeuours to preuaile, to betake themſelues to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humiliation.</hi> whereas this is the practiſe of the Saints, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their ſupplications till the Lord haue graunted, ſo to increaſe their exerciſe, the more difficult they proue the Lord to be. Firſt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am.</hi> 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 17.</note>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> beſought the Lord for his child, &amp; as it may ſeeme without faſting: then not obtaining, he ioyned faſting and watching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: thirdly, he continued the like till the ſeuenth day. Did hee in <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 161. &amp;c,</note>intend a ſeuen dayes fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in the beginning? Concerning the <hi>effi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acie of prayer and faſting,</hi> we haue the ſame Coleworts ſod againe. You talke, as if <hi>I made prayer and faſting for dispoſſeſsion, an vnwritten or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance:</hi> whereas I onely ſuppoſe, that if it were not expreſly ſet downe, yet for that it is to be collected out of the generall places of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>a.</hi> 22. 12.</note>Scripture, as where the Lord doth ſummon vs, in the day of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction vnto weeping and mourning, to baldneſſe and girding with ſackcloth: and to call vpon him in the time of our ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſitie, and ſuch like: and becauſe alſo by experience we proue it to be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, this were ſufficient warrant to vs for the ordinance of God in this behalfe. You might therefore haue ſpared your paines in proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>the ſufficiencie of the worde of God,</hi> till you mette with ſome Papiſt, in which number I tkanke the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am not.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag.</hi> 167</note> For your demaunds, <hi>If dispoſſeſsion be now ordinarie, what be the things ordinary in it.</hi> To ſatisfie you (though you litle deſerue it) for the <hi>medicine,</hi> I anſwere it is faſting and prayer: the <hi>operation,</hi> is the mightie power and wil of God, apprehended inſtrumentally by our faith: <hi>the miniſteriall hand to apply this medicine,</hi> is the aſſembly of Chriſtians gathered for this purpoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>The theorie or skill to directe this hand,</hi> is the knowledge that they bee warranted in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the worde of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>the meanes to imprint this skill in thoſe phyſitions breaſts,</hi> are the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> meanes of knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hearing, reading, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating,: <hi>the habit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f this skill</hi> is their faith, which is more confirmed by the often practiſe of the Church in all times. Nowe then, if you cannot ſee what is ordinary in this worke, bewayle your ordinarie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9803:26"/>
blinde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſe which will not ſuffer you to behold the truth. That which followeth is no leſſe fooliſh then falſe, which you taike of <hi>faiths wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ex opere operato:</hi> as alſo that <hi>faſting and prayer cure by way of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 168 <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.</note>
               <hi>miracle:</hi> that <hi>faſting and prayer is no ſupernaturall maner of cure:</hi> &amp; that <hi>if it be ſupernaturall, then it is extraordinarie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Is it poſsible for men to dote in this manner? But if the light that is in men bee darkneſſe, how great is their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>?</p>
            <p>To the teſtimonies of ancient &amp; later writers alleaged by me, you anſwer firſt, that <hi>I wreſt open their mouths, and make them ſpeak what I pleaſe.</hi> It is true, they ſpeake what I pleaſe, becauſe in this matter I ſpeak nothing but what pleaſeth thê<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but you inſinuat that I peruert them. If you could haue ſhewed one ſyllable this way, al the world ſhould haue heard of it. Beſides, you haue already teſtified in your former <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> that they ſpake, as I report the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, you ſay, <hi>they speake nothing at all to my purpoſe in hand.</hi> My purpoſe in allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them was to ſhew, firſt, that men in theſe dayes may be diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of diuels. Secondly, that faſting &amp; prayer haue bene vſed by the moſt learned and godly in the Church from time to time, ſince miracles ceaſed, for expelling of Satan out of the poſſeſſed. Nowe whether they ſpake to theſe <hi>purpoſes</hi> or no, becauſe your ſelues haue loſt your eyſight, let others that can iudge of colours ſay what they thinke. Your third anſwere is, that <hi>I haue not their owne examples or practſe, but only their bare reports concerning the practiſe of ſome others co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſing among them.</hi> This likewiſe is vntrue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> recken themſelues in the number of them which did expell diuels. And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> was preſent in the congregation, and preached two ſeueral dayes at leaſt, when publike prayers were made for expel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of Satan out of perſons poſſeſſed, brought to that ende into the Church at the commandement of the Deacon. And thereforè wee haue theſe three mens <hi>practiſe.</hi> But admit that none of them had made mention of their owne practiſe, might not their iudgment &amp; coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruent prayers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to be vſed for the healing of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed</hi> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? ſpecially ſeeing diuers of them adde, that <hi>they haue knowne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8</note>
               <hi>ſome that haue beene healed by the prayers of the godly.</hi> Fourthly, ſay you, <hi>they giue their aduiſe for the ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rciſe of prayer alone.</hi> And this is your fourth l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, for ſome of them mention prayer &amp; faſting. Thus much for reply to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our generall anſweres, let vs nowe heare thoſe which be particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. To <hi>Origen</hi> you anſwere, that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inſinuateth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mply</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 169.</note>
               <hi>the ſuppoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficacie of faſting and prayer, but putteth downe no practiſe of it as of a perpetuall ordinance.</hi> Marke how falſe lyers ſaulter in their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9803:27"/>
ſpeech. Did <hi>Origen</hi> ſuppoſe ſuch an efficacie of faſting and prayer &amp; yet not thinke it was Chriſts ordinance, and to bee vſed? Whence could it haue efficacie, but from Chriſt? Or to what purpoſe was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie, if to no vſe? He therefore that acknowledgeth the lawfull efficacie of faſting and prayer, doth alſo acknowledge, that there is an ordinance of faſting &amp; prayer to ſuch an end. <hi>Tertullian</hi> you ſay, <hi>Speakes of manie pretended deliuerances from Satan, but ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th not the maner how they were fried from them.</hi> What? doth <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apologie of Chriſtianitie againſt the Gentils, to the whole ſtate of Rome, alleage certaine counterfeit deliuerances from Satan, to countenance Chriſtian religion with? Doth he vſe ſuch policie in writing to the Gouernour <hi>Scapula,</hi> to gaine credite to the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell? Surely you are either not well in your wits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or which is worſe, you haue for filthy ſucres ſake conſpired to make but meere fables of the great works of God. <hi>But he ſheweth not,</hi> ſay you, <hi>the maner how they were deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Do you ſticke at this matter? you will not haue it by miracle in any ſort: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d therefore, ſay wee, by faſting and prayer. Nay but, will you ſay, if it were at all, it was by Miracle, and Miracles were ceaſed before his dayes. Therefore ſpeake plainely, and tell <hi>Tertullian</hi> to his face that he lyes, that hee deluded the world with his <hi>pretended deliuerances.</hi> This is your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and this anſwer would be ſhort. How <hi>Cyprian</hi> is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, <hi>we ſhall know</hi> (ſay you) <hi>by Iames Pammelius, who telleth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, That the Fxorciſts office was not then in an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vſe of the church, becauſe that office being ioyned with the gift of Miracles, did continue but for a time.</hi> I do not alleage <hi>Cyprian</hi> for the office of Exorciſts, but for the caſting forth of diuels in thoſe dayes, which he teſtifieth plainly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And the diuels by torments of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds are caſt out of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>bod es poſſeſſed.</hi> To this adde, if you will <hi>Pammelius</hi> his teſtimonie, <hi>that miracles were then ceaſed,</hi> and ſo we conclude, That there were caſting forth of diuels in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, &amp; yet not miraculous. But yet for <hi>Iames Pammelius</hi> let me tell you thus much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wheras you alleage his words <hi>for the ceaſing of Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rciſts before that time,</hi> and alſo that a little after he ſhould ſay, <hi>That the crafts and iugling ſleights of counterfeit Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yp. Epiſt, <hi>55</hi> &amp; <hi>76<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> edit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ammel. Antuerp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ad. b. Petr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elleri <hi>1589</hi>
               </note>&amp; <hi>coniuring prieſts, they are long ſince apparantly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uident: yea euen to the very eyes of the blind:</hi> I maruelled greatly to heare theſe words of <hi>Iames Pammelius:</hi> I knew he affirmes the cleane contrary, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſtrongly by teſtimony of Antiquitie that office of Exorci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing both of Spirits poſſeſsing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in Baptiſme. I turned my <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brian,</hi> but I could find no ſuch words of his. And therefore either
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9803:27"/>
you haue met with an edition later then the laſt, or els you are as notable in belying mens writinges as the moſt ſhamleſſe Papiſt of them all. To the reſt, as <hi>Chryſoſtome, Peter Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Kemnitius, Phil. Melancthon, Beza, Vogellius, Danaeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Chaſſanius,</hi> all of them moſt plainly teſtifying diſpoſſeſſion, and that by meanes of faſting and prayer, you anſwere not one word, but for the lenght of their foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, referre vs to that which hath beene ſpoken of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Indeed theſe treade in the ſteps of the former, and of all the godly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earned that went before them &amp; therfore by them we may geſſe their footings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo likewiſe by your three wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les anſwers to the three former we may eaſily geſſe what would be your anſwere to theſe, namely all the abſurd ſhiftes you could deuiſe to elude their teſtimonies, as not hauing in purpoſe to find out the truth, or to yeild to it beeing found, but by hook and by crook to maintaine your owne giddy fancies, whatſoeuer eyther Scripture, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ſaye againſt it. What doe I therfore diſputing with ſuch companions, which make not truth their end, but ſome other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe reſpect, I know not well, what? Surely Chriſtian Reader, that which I do is for thy good, to laye open vnto thee their vnconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable iuglings, leaſt by any coloured pretences thou ſhouldſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled by them Did not I well to bind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their good behauior by a publike Inſtrument in their <hi>Diſcourſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Thou ſeeſt they haue not one worde of truth to ſay againſt the practiſe of the Church of God from the Apoſtles time till now. But you are weary of theſe authenticall witneſſes and therefore betake your ſelues againe to your wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted reaſonings, where you may haue more ſcope of words, and more hope to darken the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 170.</note> 
               <hi>If,</hi> ſay you, <hi>prayer and faſting bee an eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed ordinance, then it ſhould be alwayes effectuall.</hi> I anſwere, you ſeldome bring an <hi>If</hi> but there is a lye in the end of it. The prophet complayneth, <hi>How</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 18</note>
               <hi>long Lord? wilt thou hide thy face for euer?</hi> Becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> obtained not by his ſute his Sonnes life, he might by this rule haue bid pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er and faſting adue. Infinite are the inſtances: it is meruaile you could meet with none of them, to cauſe you to hold in ſo groſſe an vntruth. But I crie you mercy, you meane effectuall in regard of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag,</hi> 171, 172, 173.</note>vttermoſt iſſue, not of the preſent time. Now then frame your rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>The ordinance of god is alwayes effectuall, prayer &amp; faſting is not allwayes effectuall, &amp; ſo not god his ordinance in this caſe.</hi> I anſwere. if you take <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffectual</hi> for the laſt iſſue and ſuch help as is expedient, you ſay vntruly of prayer and faſting: If you meane <hi>Effectuall</hi> for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9803:28"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſible, imagined and preſent helpe, then is it as falſe, you ſay of gods ordinance. And this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you mark it, will ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fice for all you prat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pa.</hi> 174. 175</note>about this matter. So likewiſe, how <hi>Dispoſſeſsion now is no miracle</hi> enough hath beene ſpoken, except you can bring vs ſomething of more weight, then hitherto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou haue done. Further ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erue that here they ſpare not to denie (though in as couert tearmes as they can) the witneſſe of <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Chryſoſtome,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of al the reſt before alleaged, or that can be. Moreouer, it this will not ſerue, for compendiouſneſſe ſake, and more ſecuritie of their cauſe, they deny the concluſion. I he argument is, <hi>If diſpoſſeſsion by prayer and faſting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 176.</note>
               <hi>be miraculou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, then Tertullian, Cyprian, Chyſoſtome, and others wrought miracles, when they expelled diuels after this ſort: but this is falſe: and therefore the firſt.</hi> To this you anſwere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Secondly, if it be true that here tofore or nowe spirits bee expelled by ſole prayer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſting, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n is the worke a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acle:</hi> which is the contrarie a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>firmation to the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 177</note>When you ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke of <hi>ſole prayer and faſting,</hi> you haue a ſecret mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of your owne of ſole prayer without faith. Concerning which I tell you again, that if <hi>M. Walker</hi> &amp; you haue ſuch a kind of prayer and ſuch a kind of faith, as vſually are ſeparated one from another, you may do well to diſpute of ſuch matters betweene your ſelues, for my part I allowe no ſuch prayer, neither doth the Church of God.</p>
            <p>You argue, <hi>that dispoſſeſsion is not by hiſtoricall or temporary faith,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 179.</note>
               <hi>becauſe God hath appointed it to miracul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us faith:</hi> which thing if it had beene proued in the beginning, we had done long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince. Further, you ſee not wherein <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying faith ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter then T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie, if this doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt out diuels,</hi> as if to caſt out diuels out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were all in all Beſides, <hi>if hiſtoricall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th be ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels might caſt out diuels.</hi> But what if they will not? you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e neuer a whit the nearer. Such trumperie ſha l haue no other anſwere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or anſwere to your fourth reaſon I ſay, a reprobate may app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l end the mercies of God the Creator<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but not of God the Redeemer, And ſuch apprehenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n for the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecting of Satan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ffice.</p>
            <p>You ſlaunder me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou ſay, that in <hi>diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion of Sommers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 182</note>
               <hi>we purpoſely prayed to teach the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>olders, that the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted by the onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower of him t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whome w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put vp ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 183. 184. 185</note>it to ſay you ſclander me? You make no more account to ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ander me, then to fillip me. Againe I doe not ſay, that <hi>parties b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hed haue no wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant from the Scripture t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faſt &amp; pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> (as is apparan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the place by you quoted, where I counſell them to this hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſe) but only, that ther is not ſuch expreſſe mention in the word
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9803:28"/>
for the curing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as for parties poſſeſſed. And therefore all that is an idle diſpute which you purpoſe for diuers pages together in this matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> haue me a companion in this wick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 186</note>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ertion, which your ſelues maintain as is apparant afterwards. But note (good reade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an egreg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous blaſphemy, that theſe <hi>Anſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>werers</hi> make t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> guiltie of the horrible ſins co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by the wicked <hi>in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>king to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ueil for help</hi> in their miſeries. For how doe they proue it to be <hi>an abſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itie to cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oples going to the diuel for helpe?</hi> Surely thus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be a ſinne to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eke help of the diuel, we ſhall make the Lord ginit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of this ſin w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whom it can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot be done.</hi> Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeſt what blaſphemie this propoſition co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for it plainly affor deth that which before I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the Concluſion, to wit, it is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nr e to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elpe of the diuel, is a concluſion of monſtrous impiet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o where they would proue, <hi>There is no warrant from the worae for prayer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſting to be vſed in behalfe of parties bewitched,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 188.</note>there argument is of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orte. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f there be no wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom the word tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſole prayer &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſting haue any power of themſelues ex opere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perato, to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upernaturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts of God, then there is no wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant for parties b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> witch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to vſe faſting and prayer as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efull in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the firſt, ſay they, is true, &amp; therfore the ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut what do you ſticke at parties bewitched? You ſhould haue inferred generally, there is no warrant nor vſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faſting and prayer at al for any thing <hi>ex opere o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erato.</hi> O men ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ken with the blindnes of Sodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich before the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, ſeek the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, and cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind it. Is it your fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you cannot tell what you auouch? Or your ſhamleſnes, that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> names ſhould be deſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uedly odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all? Or is it, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at you do ſo far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſe all the learned of this land, that you thinke there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not one man able to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cearne ſuch prod gious falſhood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retched perſons would rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed with a three cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the writinges, or wordes of any. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if that will not ſerue, it were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eete ſuch order mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be taken with you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at the Church of God ſuſtaine no damge by you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Whether I haue ſo fondly trauerſed this queſtion <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſ ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as you ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it to the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly learned to determine, to whoſe cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure I willingl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſubmit my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this &amp; in al other m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writings But as for your iudgments I paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot. Firſt make it appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you haue eyes in your owne heads<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou take vpon you to tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what is ſtraight, or croked in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anctifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our mouths b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfeſſing, your lyes, your ſclaunders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your blaſphemies, before you giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9803:29"/>
of any my doings. In the mean ſeaſon, if you will needs be bar king, I will find ſuch a bone for you to gnaw on, as ſhall bee fit for your chaps,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 191, 192 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>93.</note> Concerning the <hi>counſell</hi> I <hi>gaue for fasting and prayer,</hi> it was grounded from hence: <hi>that in all iudgements</hi> (of which kind poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is) <hi>we are called to humiliation,</hi> for which I cite in the margine an induction of diuers examples. To which you anſwere firſt, <hi>that with out particular knowledge of the iudgement, prayers could not be made in faith to remoue it:</hi> which is one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Axioms that neuer fails you, ſuch an one as <hi>Ahabs</hi> prophets were inſpired with, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they counſel led him to warre againſt <hi>Ramoth.</hi> Shall not the poore countrey ſicke man pray to God for ſome comfort in his diſtreſſe, becauſe he doth not know particularly the nature of his diſeaſe? Secondly, that the <hi>quoted Scriptures onely teſtifie the peoples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umiliation by pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, ſo oft as any ſtrange iudgement was inflicted, but proue not eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſeſsions and diſpoſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſsions by thoſe means.</hi> yet they proue the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell I gaue was warrantable, and this I content my ſelfe with. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough if my poore premiſes afforde mee one naturall and orderly concluſion at one time. Euery mans Cow can not bring forth colts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as yours do.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ag.</hi> 194. 95, 196.</note> To conclude, you tell vs <hi>your great confidence in the cauſe,</hi> which no man needs to doubt of, if he conſider your former arrogant bold neſſe: nor much maruell at as ſtrange, if he call to minde your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible blindneſſe. But if your learning and conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce were more, your confidence would be a great deale leſſe. Then you in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erre of the premiſes, <hi>That if there be no poſſeſsion, nor diſpoſſeſsion nowe by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and prayer, how greatly they haue erred that haue auouched it, and how much they are to be blamed which cannot endure it ſhould be impug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned:</hi> But contrariwiſe ſay I, if all theſe things be true, which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, as hath beene prooued by ſtronger reaſon, then you poſsibly withſtand, what doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou deſerue which haue troubled the Church with newe and ſingular opinions in theſe points, and in broaching them, haue offered to the world to choke them withall other verie many groſſe, fantaſticall and impious abſurdities? and yet you dare intitle your fooleries, <hi>The infallible truth,</hi> and ſuch, as <hi>Glory &amp; praiſe is to be giuen to toe Lord for theſe his lately reuealed counſels by you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe intricate queſtions.</hi> O intolerable proud ignorance! Haue you by <hi>late reuelation</hi> cleared theſe intricate queſtions? Indeed your aſſertions be late<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for they were neuer heard of in the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but they were neuer reuealed vnto you by the Spirit of truth,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9803:29"/>
but by that lying ſpirit, whoſe image doth liuely appeare almoſt in euery argument you handle. And yet that my ſelfe be not onely iudge, let any man of vnderſtanding waigh with equal balance that litle that hath beene <hi>replyed,</hi> &amp; compare it with yours, &amp; then giue ſentence: whether any ſince the time of our peace by our gratious Queene, profeſſing the goſpell, hath publiſhed any writing of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie that doth come neare theſe your treatiſes in number of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound potions, in miſconſtructions &amp; wreſtings of Scriptures, in abſured collections, in impudent reiecting the authoritie of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, in ſhameleſſe pretending the names of good authours againſt their owne meanings, in childiſh ſtumbling in the firſt rudiments of Arts, in moſt frequent lying and ſlaundering, and which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of all, in dangerous and ſcandalous aſſertions mixed with ſome notorious blaſphemies: and then it may be you ſhall carie the bell of al that haue written in our times. Great cauſe there is we ſhould all make bonefires for the publiſhing of your bookes, or rather of your publiſhed bookes: but eſpecially <hi>M. Biſhop,</hi> who got the priuiledge ad <hi>imprimendum ſolum,</hi> I beleeue he beſhrewes your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="treatise">
            <head>A REPLIE TO THE THIRD DIALOGVE.</head>
            <p>YOur <hi>Vſes</hi> are ſutable to your doctrine. For what other thing can proceede from a Cockatrices egge, then a ſerpent? Yet <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canthropus</hi> admires and applaudes them: and ſo perhaps may ſome <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 27</note>doe, that be not well in their wits. But they which haue receiued the annointing, that teacheth vs concerning all things, will abhorre your prodigious dotage, and the more when they conſider your vſes, which manifeſt plainly that your errours be not about ſtrawes and ruſhes, ſuch as without danger might be contemned and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but which draw after them moſt perillous conſequences, migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tily ſhaking the verie foundation, and chiefeſt pillers of our faith. You pretend that this <hi>your doctrine of finall determination of poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; dispoſſeſſions of Spirits and Diuels,</hi> affordeth firſt, <hi>an holy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation concerning the vndoubted faithfulneſſe and truth of our eternall God, in that he promiſing four thouſand years fully before, to ſend the ſeed of a woman, which ſhould bruiſe the ſerpents head, hath in his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9803:30"/>
time fulfilled the ſame, by ſending his ſonne.</hi> We beleeue and know it, that not one iote of the Lordes promiſe hath failed, but doth your doctrine yeeld any confirmation of it? Nay verily, but doth vtterly ouerthrow it, and make the Lord of truth to haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified his word. The Lord hath promiſed by ſending his ſonne fully to ſubdue and vanquiſh Satan: your doctrine doth teach vs, that Chriſt by his death hath onely made an end of poſſeſsions and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſsions of diuels, that is, that he hath only deliuered <hi>Demoniaks</hi> ſuch as were actually tormented in their bodies by the Diuels. What? Are all the Elect Demoniakes? Haue you not taught vs. that Poſſeſsions were very rare before Chriſts time, and that it was verie probable there were none at all in Iſrael, till a little before his comming, and none after the Apoſtles? Are only then theſe men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by Chriſts death? You haue quit the Lord indeed wel of his promiſe. He promiſed the breaking of Satans head, you make that Chriſt hath ſcarce pulled one lock of haire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head. He promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed deliuerance for al his elect, you reſtrain this deliuerance only to m enactually poſſeſt with diuells. He promiſed vs a gift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were of an hundreth thouſand talents: you make him to haue ſatisfied his promiſe in beſtowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon vs an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth pence. Do men ſatisfy bondes in ſuch manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doth a Creditor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to whome is owing a thouſand pound, hold himſelfe contented in receauing two or thre ſhillinges. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye vpon your comfort: you are miſerable comforters: But this determination<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſay, of Satans <hi>Actuall poſſeſſion may confirme faith and hope for the vtter ſubuerſion of the whole kingdom of darknes.</hi> I anſwer, you ly falſly, if your doctrine be true. For hope can expect no more then faith doth preſently imbrace, but by your teaching, faith doth not imbrace a ful vanguiſhing of ſatans kingdome by Chriſts death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but onely an end of Actual poſſeſſions (which neither was accompliſhed, as hath bene ſhewed) and therfore hope cannot looke for any further ſubuerſion of Satans kingdome then is alredie. Now let the godly iudge what lyeth hiden in your doctrine, whether they be things to be tolerated, and cooly dealt in or no: or rather of ſuch nature, that if you will not reclaime them, all louers of the truth ought to ſpit in your faces in deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of your errours. So likewiſe when you ſpeak of God his al ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciencie, of Chriſts triumph, and of the Diuels captiuitie, who ſo euer truſts to your doctrine in theſe poynts, ſhall perceaue he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vpon a ſtaffe of reede, which when hee ſhall ſtand in neede of it will brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a ſunder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and run through his body, as may ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9803:30"/>
be ſeene by this little, that I haue nowe remembred, as alſo by that hath beene more fully declared, in Suruey of your Sixt Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. your vſes then are wretched, and therefore I leaue them.</p>
            <p>The proper vſe that can be made of your doctrine is, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould now ſhew their wiſedome in practiſing that rule our Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt hath taught them, namely this, <hi>beware of ſalſe prophets which come to you in ſheepes clothing, but inwardly they are rauening</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 15</note>
               <hi>wolues.</hi> Thou haſt ſeene in this book of theirs, good Reader, theſe men profeſſing themſelues, <hi>The Lord his vnworthiest on earth:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to three of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſtles.</note>when they beginne their diſputations, to begin the ſame with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, recreating themſelues with ſinging of <hi>pſalmes:</hi> to wiſh the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend brethren if they haue faulted either in matter or mannerto confute them and spare not, withall</hi> deſiring <hi>the bleſſing of God to light on their hearts for their labour that way: to haue</hi> vſed many <hi>wordes of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dial. Diſcou pag. <hi>7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 262.</hi> Epiſt. Dedi. Anſ.</note>
               <hi>goodly pretence, of great obedience to the</hi> magiſtrate, of great care of their brethrens good, of great ſynceritie in calling euery thing to the triall of the Scripture, and many ſuch other faire ſhewes. On the other ſide thou may ſt ſee by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this <hi>Suruey</hi> and <hi>Reply</hi> what abundance of vile and groſſe errors is packed vp in theſe their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, What litle conſcience they make of god his truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Of lying &amp; ſlandering, how exceedingly they haue trifled in ech ſeuerall poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nt, and now by theſe vſes how all tendes to this, to deſcredit God his truth in fulfilling his promiſe, to impeach his ſufficiency for van quiſhing of fatan, to reſtrain Chriſts triumph to a thing of nothing, to limit Satans captiuitie with looſing of a skonſe, and ſuch like: which thinges beeing thus, now it will ſhortly and eaſily more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, whither theſe men be falſe prophets, or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if they ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cant themſelues of their errours, and as they haue giuen publike ſcandall to the Church, in labouring to draw men after their fan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cies, ſo againe in ſubmiſſion to the truth, diſclame all ſuch opinio n diſſonant from the ſacred word, throwing the firſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one at themſelues, to the end all other may beware of them, then they ſhall be manif eſted to haue ſhipped but of infirmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, and to be ſuch indeed, as they would ſeeme. Otherwiſe if they will ſtill maintaine &amp; defend them, then thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeſt good reader, theſe mens ſheepes clothing, and how for thy ſake I haue pulled it ouer their eares, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt behold them to be inwardly rauening woules: if they be to be iudged wolues, not only which rent the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of our bodies in ſunder, but alſo &amp; much more they, which by infecting men with peſtiferous opinions, deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſaran to be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9803:31"/>
torne in peeces both bodies and ſoules<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In this caſe it will behooue the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, both Ciuill &amp; Eccleſiaſticall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to take or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, that ſuch cruel deucuring beaſts may be driuen from Chriſts fold: &amp; that they would conſider, that they make not diſſenſions &amp; ſcandales contrary to the doctrine we haue learned, which ſtand for the truth, but they which oppugne the truth. It is the rebell that makes ciuil war: the faithful ſubiects wepons are not agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the peace but for the peace, neither is it the dog barki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in the night, that diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiets the ſhepheardes, but the Wolues approching: the kepers ſtir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring is to be commended, &amp; the theues aſſaulting he is to be defend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. This vſe then the Magiſtrate is to make of your doctrine: ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all the Chriſtians of this land, are to take it as a watchword to auoyd you as Scorpions, that they may know you to be men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hil.</hi> 3. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud.</hi> 16.</note>which haue made your bellies your god, &amp; to glory in your ſhame: which haue a forme of godlynes &amp; haue denied the power of it, whoſe mouthes ſpeake proude things, hauing the perſons of men in admiration for aduantage ſake. Theſe manner of men are fortold ſhould come in theſe laſt dayes, &amp; our Church doth already feele it by lamentable experience. If thou ſhalt make this vſe, Chriſtian rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19</note>of their booke it ſhall not bee altogether vnprofitable for thee. For <hi>It muſt needes be that hereſies ſhould come, that they which are appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued amongst vs may be knowne.</hi> The Lord therefore ſtrengthen vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſo many as be of this number, to ſtand for his truth, and giue, vs wiſe dome to diſcerne thoſe which would craftily vndermine it, that all ſuch wicked workers beeing defeated, wee may conſtantly walke in the puritie of it, till the day of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, to whom, with the father and the holy Spirit be all honour and praiſe for euer.</p>
            <p>Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:31"/>
            <head>Here foloweth my anſwere to the Contradictions they charge mee with.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>contradicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 13.</note> The <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> charging me with a ſhamfull companie of <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> no leſſe then fiftie, I firſt framed an anſwere to them, with full purpoſe to publiſh it, &amp; therein haue made it plaine there is not a contradiction. But this my Treatiſe prouing much larger then I intended, &amp; the anſwere to them being of litle or no vſe, ſaue only to cleare my ſelfe of this ſlaunder, and to diſcouer their filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which needeth not, I thought good rather to ſuppreſſe, then publiſh it: yet ſo as I will giue thee, good Reader, a taſte thereof, and of their vpright dealing herein, aſſuring, thee of my credit, that euen ſuch be the reſt of their contradictions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> Darell, <hi>ſay they,</hi> in his <hi>Doctrine</hi> pag. <hi>54.</hi> ſaith, that prayer and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting being vſed aright, will certainly proſper either to the remouing or ſanctifying of the iudgment. But pag. <hi>56.</hi> he ſaith, their is no aſſurance to preuaile.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>contrad.</hi> 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> I anſwere. There is no aſſurance to preuaile, that is, <hi>we can not be ſure the partie ſhall be deliuered, the meanes being vſed,</hi> for ſo are my wordes. Had then I ſayd <hi>pag.</hi> 54. <hi>faſting will certainlie proſper to the remouing of the iudgement,</hi> and no more, I had contradicted that I ſay, <hi>pag,</hi> 59 but adding <hi>or ſanctifying,</hi> a child may ſee here is no con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tradiction. Such a contradiction is this: Certenly the <hi>Diſcourſers</hi> wil ether be aſhamed of their contradictions, or their ſinne is the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter: Aſſuredly they will not be aſhamed of their contradictions. And this: The ſun is either vnder a cloud, or ſet. It is not vnder a cloud.</p>
            <p>In his Detection <hi>163.</hi> Darrell ſaith, fire hath powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to burne, &amp; in the ſame pag. hath no power to burne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> All that we reade <hi>Detection</hi> 163. is that <hi>Somers hand being in the fire was not burnt.</hi> Would euer any man, theſe two excepted, hence collect <hi>a contradiction?</hi> How many thouſands in this land haue ſaid the ſame, and among them not a few that be learned, &amp; yet I dare ſay neither learned, nor vnlearned euer feared they ſpake contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech, &amp; Abednego</hi> being in the fire were not bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and yet they that caſt them into the fire were burnt. I truſt you wil not ſay here is a <hi>contradiction.</hi> But confeſſe both theſe to be true. Fire naturally burneth, but reſtrayned by God the ouer-ruler o nature, it doth not burne. Secondly, you ſhould firſt haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where I ſay, <hi>Fire hath power to burne,</hi> before you told vs that I ſpeake contraries.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9803:32"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntrad.</hi> 24.</note> In his <hi>Dotrine</hi> pag. <hi>2.</hi> he ſaith, that it ſuteth altogether with Satans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ature to be filthie or wicked in ſpeech. But <hi>Detection 175.</hi> he ſaith, that it ſutethe as well with his nature to vſe good and holy speeches.</p>
            <p>My wordes <hi>Detection</hi> 175. <hi>be, Holy wordes haue beene vttered by ſatan.</hi> Tel me is this a falſe propoſition? Or yet this: <hi>vncleane and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Anſ.</note>
               <hi>blasphemous ſpeeches ſute excellently with the nature of the vncleane spirit.</hi> If both theſe be true, which none will deny, with what truth doe you ſay that I ſpeake <hi>contraries,</hi> whereof the one muſt needs be falſe? Theſe men ſure had forgot when they doted of this <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> that the diuel is as well by nature ſubtil, (and in his ſubtiltie <hi>ready to transforme</hi> him ſelfe into Angel of light) as vncleane and wicked. Of this ſtampe they haue 18 contradictions more.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>Doctrine 47.</hi> He ſaith the diſciples by vertue of their ſo large <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontrad:</hi> 11,</note>a commiſſion could caſt out a diuel of any kinde. But pag. <hi>50.</hi> the Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike child was poſſeſt with one of the worſt kinde of ſpirits, and that thence it came the diſciples could not caſt him out.</p>
            <p>To make this <hi>contradiction</hi> they haue <hi>detracted</hi> part of my words <note place="margin">Anſ,</note>in either propoſition. In the former theſe, <hi>if their faith failed not:</hi> which words, or words to the ſame effect in the aforeſaid <hi>pag.</hi> 47. &amp; the two <hi>pages</hi> precedent I vſe no leſſe then twelue times. In the latter propoſition where I ſay, <hi>thence partly it came,</hi> they <hi>detract</hi> this word <hi>partly:</hi> wherby I intimate the Diſciples faith did at that time faile them, when they could not caſt the diuel out of the lunatike child, ſo that their incredulitie was one let, which oft els where I expreſſe. And this you well knewe, as appeareth by your next <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,</hi> the twelft I meane. What meant you then thus to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and rent aſunder thoſe words which of purpoſe I had coupled together? And by <hi>detracting</hi> that which in either of the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo materiall, and in the one I <hi>inculcate</hi> ſo often, to pretend a contradiction where you knew none was? Who hath bewitched you to vſe ſuch curled deuiſes, for the compaſſing of your contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions? A curſed pretence muſt this needes be, ſeeing it can not be done in ignorance: For you cannot be ignorant hereof, that the wordes detracted by you I vſed, ſpcially thoſe ſo oft iterated, and that in thoſe <hi>pages</hi> from whence yee haue the ſa de contradictorie propoſition: conſidering alſo that to make another contradiction you aleag the very ſame words you omit here, &amp; that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame page, as witneſſeth the contradiction here following. Neither can you be ignorant of this, that theſe wordes being vſed and added by me, I am not contrary to my ſelfe, yea hence it is that you did
<pb facs="tcp:9803:32"/>
omit them. It muſt needes therfore be that you knowing here was no <hi>contradiction,</hi> haue againſt that knowledge of yours (by this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of <hi>detracting</hi> theſe words) made yet a faire ſhew to the world of a contradiction. Here is no contrarietie except theſe be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions contradictory: <hi>The Diſciples could caſt out a diuell of any kind, if their faith fayled not: The Diſciples their faith failing could not caſt the diuell out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>contrad,</hi> 31</note> In his <hi>Doctrine 47.</hi> he ſaith the Apoſtles faith failed not: But pag. <hi>48</hi> he ſaith it failed at this time when Chriſt ſpake to them and in this very worke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſ,</note> Theſe wordes, <hi>the Apoſtles ſaith failed not,</hi> you could omit, when ſuch omiſſion ſerueth for your purpoſe, as appeares by the former contradiction. But now when they muſt ſtand you in ſome ſteade, they are not to ſeeke. He wanteth the vſe of one of his ſences, that ſmelleth not here your ſtinking breath. My wordes be theſe. They <hi>were able to caſt out al diuels, if their faith fayled not:</hi> which imply not <hi>that the Apoſtles faith neuer failed them,</hi> as you would haue it, for otherwiſe here is no contradiction, but rather the contrary, that their faith did at ſome times faile them. Again, though theſe words <hi>The Apoſtles faith failed not,</hi> with the former are mine, yet thus rent and ſeparated from their fellowes, I may trulye ſay they are not mine. In your <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> you ſay, <hi>if the skies fall we ſhall haue larks,</hi> By your wiſe rule you there affirme, that <hi>the skies do falle</hi> &amp; in the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e booke <hi>pag.</hi> 24. where you haue theſe words: <hi>If Angels be vncrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted then are they eternall:</hi> you affirme, that <hi>Angels be vncreated:</hi> yet <hi>pag.</hi> 28. you ſay <hi>Angels be created.</hi> Theſe propoſitions be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie, and the former of them abſurd, and ſo here is a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (forſooth) and an abſurditie, when indeed there is neither. Here is paltrie and childiſh ſtuffe. If I would walke but in this one croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſtep of yours, how eaſily could I make a booke of your <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> and another of your abſurdities. But ſuppoſe I had ſaid no more then you produce. vz. <hi>The Apoſtles faith ſailed not</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence ye could not inferre a contradiction, except I had ſpoken of the ſame time me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in the latter contradictorie propoſition. Their, faith might not falle them at one time, and yet ſaile them at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>contrad,</hi> 15,</note> 
               <hi>In Doctrine 52</hi> Abrahams prayer is made a ſole meanes of conception and procreation of chidren: But pag. <hi>60</hi> another meanes is found appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of God for that purpoſe, or els it would proue a miracle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſ,</note> As before by detracting ſo here by adding you abuſe both mee,
<pb facs="tcp:9803:33"/>
and the Reader: The words I vſe be theſe <hi>Who will deny but that as the ſinne of Abimilech (in taking Sarah, Abrahams wife vnto him) had ſhut vp euery wombe of the houſe of Abimelech, ſo the pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was the meane whereby they were opened. &amp; that iudgement taken away?</hi> Do I here make <hi>Abrahams prayer a ſole meanes of procreation?</hi> That I meane &amp; affirme is, that by <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayer as a meanes <hi>Abimelech</hi> his wyfe &amp; women ſeruants, were made able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, which before they could not, not excluding, but including the knowlege and ſeede of man: which no man in his right minde would hence gather, this couple excepted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urad,</hi> 46,</note> In his Doctrine pag. <hi>2.</hi> he ſaith, it is abſurd to affirme that the diuel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being without a man) can diſpoſe of the whole or any parte of mans bodie: but Detection, page <hi>11.</hi> he ſaith that thediuel (in all probability) did vſe Sommers his tongue, notwithſtanding he was eſſentiallie and ſenſiblic playing boe peepe vnder the couerleed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſ,</note> The former propoſition is not mine, <hi>I ſay euery part,</hi> you ſave, <hi>any part.</hi> And ſo by <hi>altering</hi> a word you haue made <hi>a contradic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion</hi> where none is: except there be no other part of <hi>Sommers</hi> his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, beſides his tongue.</p>
            <p>And thus to thee Reader, but for breuitie, I would make it eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that of the <hi>diſcourſers</hi> fiftie contradictions, being examined one by one, there is not ſo much as one to be found. The greater is their ſiune and ſhame who charged me with ſo many.</p>
            <p>And here we are to obſeruefirſt, that of theſe contradic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions there are aboue 20. wherin there is no contradiction at all, taking them at the huckſters hand, euen as themſelues haue quoted them. And namely theſe: contradiction 4. 6. 7. 8. 13. 14. 17. 18. 19. 21. 23. 24. 26. 28. 31. 35. 38. 36. 37. 41, &amp; 45</p>
            <p>Secondly, to marke the ſeueral deuiſes or ſleights whereby they make ſemblance of contradictions when there are indeed none if you take the words as they be ſet downe in my treatiſes. I his ſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blance they make.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By <hi>forging</hi> that I neuer affirmed (but often the contrary) as in contradiction 1. 9. 17. 19. 20, 23, 25, 26, 27, 35, &amp; 46.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>By omitting</hi> or <hi>detracting</hi> ſome worde or words material, as <hi>in contradiction</hi> 3, 11, 12, 25, 27, 30, 31, 33, 36, 39, &amp; 40</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>By adding,</hi> and thus haue they done in contradiction 15. 43. &amp; 47.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:9803:33"/>
4 By <hi>altering,</hi> as apeareth by contradiction 6, 17, 27, 29, 49</p>
            <p n="5">5 To this ſaid end alſo, when both their contradictory propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions are in the ſame <hi>page,</hi> and ſomtimes in the very ſame ſentence, they runne notwithſtanding for the one of them to a <hi>page</hi> far off, or happelie to another booke: Hereby (I meane by alleaging two diſtinct pages of mine, ſomwhat alſo aſunder) pretending, that what I ſay n one place, forgetting forſooth my ſelf, I gaynſay in another. As appeareth by contradiction 1. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26. 36. 42. &amp; 47.</p>
            <p>Thus haue theſe men ſo accuſtomed and taught themſelues to falſife my writings in whole or in part: by <hi>forging, detracting, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; altering,</hi> as they haue alleaged very litle of mine truly: &amp; no marce: becauſe truly alleaged they would not make for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Yet notwithſtanding they haue by theſe curſed meanes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed their <hi>contradictions,</hi> I doubt not but that they pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues greatly, and glory in them, ſpecially in the great number of them, and doe thinke therein they haue ſhewed not a litle wit. But I <hi>will</hi> tel you, a very foole that will giue libertie to himſelf to <hi>adde, detract</hi> and <hi>alter</hi> but here &amp; there a letter, may eaſily make, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>contradictions,</hi> where none are: much more he that wil do thus by wordes &amp; ſomtimes by ſentences, as you haue done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſ. Epiſt, to the Reader fol, <hi>4</hi>
               </note> VVhether now you haue <hi>pretermited any thing material,</hi> and by ſuch <hi>omitting,</hi> and <hi>taking what parte of my writings might make moſt for your purpoſe, euen purpoſely maymed my writings,</hi> which you deny and I affirme, iudge thou indiſſirently betwene vs good reader. And whether you will <hi>acknowledge</hi> and <hi>redreſſe the offred wrong,</hi> whereof I complaine, and which I truſt to be a <hi>wrong</hi> I haue made manifeſt by this my <hi>Replie,</hi> vnto all men, &amp; to your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as you pretend you will, nay, ſeeme to abhorre not to do it, if once the <hi>wrong</hi> ſhal be made to appeare, ſaying: <hi>God forbid that we ſhould not doe it very willinglie:</hi> in time both thou and I ſhall know. And thus much for anſwer to their ſuppoſed <hi>contradictions.</hi> For bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitie ſake I omit my reply to the <hi>Abſurdities</hi> wherewith you charge me, and your ſlaunders conteined in them.</p>
            <p>Here not vnfitly may I charge you with the <hi>contradictions &amp; Abſurdities</hi> I find in your writinges: and if it fall out ſo that your ſelues be found faultie in that, wherof vniuſtly you accuſe another, then thereby learne henceforward to plucke rather the beame out of your own eyes, then buſie your ſelues ſo much about leſſe then a mote in your brothers eye.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9803:34"/>
               <hi>In their</hi> Anſwere <hi>page 55 and page 179 of their</hi> Diſcourſes, <hi>they ſay, that</hi> the manifeſtation of Chriſt his deitie, and declaration of his glorious &amp; ſpell, were the maine ends of poſſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſsion: <hi>and a little after, that</hi> the poſſeſsion of diuels were especially for theſe two ends: <hi>therby in ſinuating that there were ſome other ends or end. Yet page 67 of the ſame booke they ſay, that</hi> theſe were the two only ends of this von<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull iudgement.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2 In their</hi> Dial. diſ. <hi>page 58 they ſay,</hi> angels doe euermore worke after an inuiſible, inſenſible, and spirituall maner. <hi>And the next leafe, page 60 they ſay, that</hi> angels in all their ambaſſages they do other manifeſt themſelues by ſeeing and hearing, or aſſiſt vs eſtſoon<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s by ſome other ſenſible means. <hi>And they bring</hi> Auguſtine <hi>flatly affirming</hi> that the angels do outwardly helpe vs by certaine viſible apparitions or ſights, which they propoſe and offer before our eyes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 In their</hi> Diſcourſes <hi>pa. 42 they ſay,</hi> the mind it ſelfe, and it only is that wherein motion conſiſteth: and the body is but the minds organon or inſtrument, hauing naturally in it ſelfe no motion at all, or no further motion at the moſt, then for thoſe only actions wherin the ſaid mind (whoſe organon it is) imployeth the ſame. <hi>But in pag. 74 of the ſame booke they affirme, that</hi> the body it ſelfe hath, and may accompliſh or effect corporall operations and motions by it ſelfe alone, without anie the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, moderation, guidance, or <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 In their</hi> Diſcourſes <hi>pag. 116 they ſay,</hi> the diuell did ſo bewitch and charme the Serpent, as that (through his craftie ſuggeſtion) ſhee was very wel able to propound ſuch a diuination or ſoothſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing, as d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently circumuent or deceiue Fuah. <hi>And in the ſame booke page 1 9 they ſay, that</hi> a reaſonable speech cannot poſsibly bee framed or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of anie but of a mind hauing vnderſtanding and reaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5 In their</hi> Anſwer <hi>pa 50 they ſay.</hi> Theſe eight d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>moniakes might be poſſeſſed, though the diuell was not eſſentially inherent in anie one of their bodies: <hi>But page 43 of the ſame booke they ſay,</hi> The p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeſsion of diuels whatſoeuer is ceaſed long ſince.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6 In their</hi> Diſcourſes <hi>173 they ſay.</hi> The Apoſtles might authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tically auouch for inſallible truth whatſoeuer they preached. <hi>But in their.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere <hi>page 126 128 129 130 they ſay, that</hi> the apoſtles ſometime failed in doctrine. <hi>And a little after:</hi> all theſe were their err<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and iudgement. <hi>And againe.</hi> It was expedient for the apoſtles to erre in ſome things, <hi>that is, ſome points of doctrine.</hi> And <hi>this they
<pb facs="tcp:9803:34"/>
vnderſtand after the holy Ghoſt fell vpon them, as is plaine by the aforeſaid pages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7 In their</hi> Anſwer pag. <hi>7, they ſay, that</hi> wonders and miracles are flatly confounded: <hi>but in their</hi> Dialogicall diſcourſes <hi>209, they ſay,</hi> the diuel may worke wonders, but can effect no miracles. And pag, <hi>310, thus,</hi> A thing effected by eſſentiall means, howſoeuer it may be a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet no miracle in any respect.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8 In your</hi> Diſcourſes pag. <hi>352.</hi> for your parts you aſſure me, that you are very farre from all ſuſpition of a precompacted confederacie betweene Sommers and me. <hi>Yet in</hi> page <hi>42.</hi> of your Anſwere <hi>you ſay,</hi> why ſhould we wonder at all, that two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unning compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns <hi>(Meaning</hi> Sonnners <hi>and my ſelfe)</hi> conſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rate together before ſhould conclude ſuch a courſe betweene themſelues, as the one (by the helpe of the other) ſhould progm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icate ſtrange and mered<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble euents.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9 In pag. 39. of their</hi> Diſcourſes, <hi>they tell vs,</hi> There is not anie one ſound Diuine that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n t vnderstand Poſſeſſion as they doe, and none as I fondly imagine <hi>and yet in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſtle to the Reader prefixed before that booke, that which they deliuer</hi> concerning poſſeſſion and d spoſſ ſſion of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uels, they call, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t priuate opinion: <hi>and in page 195 of their Anſwere,</hi> The Lord his lately revealed counſels.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Part of their abſurd and vnſound Poſitions</head>
               <p n="1">1 Godby good Angels may effect fantaſticall, vaine, and filthie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <hi>Anſwers</hi> 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngels may effect vaine and filthy effects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ibid.</p>
               <p n="3">3 VVhereſoeuer the Scriptures ſpeake of Angels or diuels, they ſpeake only by metaphore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ibid.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The Diuel hath no deſire to be in any mans body. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 22</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Iewes in Chriſts time did (partly) know the parties which were poſſeſſed, from the often reuelation of the parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>anſw.</hi> 32</p>
               <p n="6">6 Godby his Spirit inſtructed the Cananitiſh woman (mentioned <hi>Matth.</hi> 15, 22) of her daughters malacie. <hi>anſw<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 33</p>
               <p n="7">7 The manifeſtation of Chriſts deitie, and the confirmation of the Goſpell, the only ends of Poſſeſsion. <hi>anſw.</hi> 67</p>
               <p n="8">8 Chriſt hath put a finall end to the poſſeſsion of diuels by his death and reſurrection. <hi>anſw.</hi> 66</p>
               <p n="9">9 The ſupernaturall actions or effects of the Diuel in Demoniaks, cannot poſsibly be comprehended by humane ſenſes. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 69</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9803:56"/>
10 The working of miracles was only in Chriſt and his Apoſtles dayes, <hi>anſw.</hi> 90</p>
               <p n="11">11 God hath appointed plowing and ſowing for a meanes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance or barrennes vpon the ground, <hi>anſw</hi> 172</p>
               <p n="12">12 Good angels do euormore worke after an inviſible, inſenſible and ſpirituall manner, <hi>Dialogical diſcourſes</hi> 58. This is to bee refuted by all thoſe places where angels are ſaid to haue appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſpoken in viſible formes vnto men.</p>
               <p n="13">13 The body hath, and may accompliſh by her ſelfe alone, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall actions and motions, without anie her ſoules direction, moderation, guidance, or conſent, <hi>Dial. diſc.</hi> 74</p>
               <p n="14">14 The dead carcaſſe of a man, or the body being ſeparate from the ſoule, may and doth alſo effect corporall actions and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. ibid.</p>
               <p n="15">15 The Diuel did ſo bewitch and ſo charme the Serpent, as that (through his craftie ſuggeſtion) ſhee was very well able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſuch a diuination or ſoothſaying, as did preſently circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uent and deceiue <hi>Euah. Dial. diſc.</hi> 16. Abſurd, that the Diuell ſhould not onely thus make the Serpent it ſelfe to ſpeake, but alſo argue the matter like a reaſonable creature</p>
               <p n="16">16 The apoſtles erred in ſome points of doctrine, after the holy Ghoſt fell vpon them: Yea, it was expedient for them ſo to erre <hi>anſw.</hi> 126, 128, 129, 130</p>
               <p n="17">17 It is verie erronious for able to imagin, that the eyes may poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſibly be deceiued, in diſcerning betweene ſpirits (that is, bodies aſſumed by ſpirits) and true naturall bodies. <hi>Dial. diſc.</hi> 157. You forget that <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> were deceiued, as appeareth by <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. and 19.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>I am to craue thy patience good Reader, ſpecially the authours, for the late comming forth of this booke: for I confeſſe it hath layen in my hands almoſt this halfe yeare.</p>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:36"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:9803:37"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9803:37"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9803:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9803:38"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9803:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:39"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:9803:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:9803:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:9803:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:41"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9803:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9803:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9803:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:9803:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9803:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:9803:44"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:9803:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9803:45"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9803:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:9803:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:9803:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:9803:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:9803:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:9803:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:9803:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:9803:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9803:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9803:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9803:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:9803:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9803:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
